<catalog><body>
 
  <sections>From the Editors</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
    <hedline>Two &lsquo;Fords,&rsquo; two fates, two leaders undone by their virtues</hedline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_EDIT02.jpg"></photo>
  <photo.caption>Rob Ford and Alison Redford: If you buy the steak, you get the gristle with the sizzle</photo.caption>
    
  <photo.byline>Chris Young/CP</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Toronto Mayor Rob Ford: thrown out of office over the consequences of using it to raise $3,150 for his youth football charity. Alberta Premier Alison Redford: not thrown out of office, and not likely to be, over her handling of a $10-billion tobacco lawsuit. Yes, the troubles of these oddly paired cross-country mirror images are very different in scale. But both, to some degree, have bogged down over conflicts of interest not just because of their actions but because of their very identities. One could argue that, like Shakespearean heroes, they have been undone by their virtues. </p>
    
    
    <p>Ford, the single-minded, ebullient football coach, charged ahead and shrugged off warnings from the city&rsquo;s integrity commissioner and the Speaker about his conflict in a council vote, leaving a judge with no choice but to punish him. Redford, a product of the ultra-small world of the Alberta bar, simply doesn&rsquo;t seem to have imagined there would be controversy over choosing her ex-husband&rsquo;s law firm to manage a massive tobacco lawsuit while she was justice minister of the province. As even her defenders observe, that&rsquo;s just how business is done there. (Which would seem to be an argument for letting somebody from another province choose among bidders for giga-contracts.) </p>
    
    <p>Toronto voted for Ford, by and large, because it wanted a renegade mayor who wouldn&rsquo;t be a prisoner of city hall. Alberta voted for Redford, by and large, because it was tired of self-taught outsiders; it was ready to welcome back a premier from the right side of Calgary&rsquo;s tracks. You buy the steak, you get the gristle as well as the sizzle. </p>
    
    <p>Predictably, the two beleaguered &ldquo;Fords&rdquo; are bringing out the worst in their supporters. Mayor Ford&rsquo;s original offence may have been penny-ante. But he missed a lot of opportunities to make things right, insisting that he could not see what he had done wrong; ignoring a formal &#64257;nding that he did do wrong, along with plenty of subsequent warnings; and, eventually, participating in a vote of council on the subject of his own punishment. There are good reasons for provincial law to be particularly nitpicky when it comes to municipal officials, and any Ontarian who disagrees needs to peek next door at Quebec. </p>
    
    <p>And please, let us hear no more about an unelected judge thwarting the &ldquo;democratic will.&rdquo; An election isn&rsquo;t an unconditional permanent ticket to power. All elected officials are faced with continuing eligibility criteria, whether formal or purely moral. Our system of government depends on the premise that statutes are re&#64258;ections of &ldquo;democratic will&rdquo; at least as much as particular personnel. </p>
    
    <p>And the judge in Ford&rsquo;s case generously left the mayor eligible to participate in the ensuing by-election should his appeal fail, essentially leaving the final disposition of the matter in the hands of the public. Couldn&rsquo;t one argue that this should happen more often at all levels of government? Throw a few of the bums out at random every six months! Make them fight their way back! </p>
    
    <p>Being toppled on a technicality may turn out to be the best thing ever to happen to Ford&mdash;both his cause and his character. It is harder to see this being true of Redford&rsquo;s difficulties, although she has probably violated no written rule. Ex-husbands, particularly those one received a divorce from 21 years ago, don&rsquo;t appear in Alberta conflict-of-interest law. But Redford&rsquo;s ex, Robert Hawkes, served as the leader of her transition team when she became premier. And, anyway, Redford did not choose to defend herself on those grounds; she fell back on the technicality that the final-final decision on the tobacco suit was left to her successor at the Justice ministry, Verlyn Olson, who took over after she picked a &ldquo;preferred bid&rdquo; from among three contenders and exited the ministry. This opened her to an argument over privilege in the assembly and created embarrassment for the new Conservative Speaker, Gene Zwozdesky, when he was forced to scurry for a pretext to kill the debate. </p>
    
    <p>The real scandal might be that governments are suing tobacco companies for &ldquo;health care costs&rdquo; at all. The newspapers are full of stories about how longer lifespans among retirees are crushing public treasuries, yet somehow we accept that tobacco companies owe governments more money because tobacco users die younger. Very well: granting that premise, why not simply crank up the tobacco tax (already $5 a pack in Alberta) to match the estimated liability? Whether won in court or taken by fiat, most of the cost burden will be passed on to addicts. But only in the former case do trial lawyers get their snouts in the trough.</p>
    
    
     </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Letters</sections>
   
   <body.head>
   
   <hedline>Letters</hedline>
   
   </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_LETTERS22.jpg"></photo>
  <photo.byline>Alan Majchrowicz/Getty Images</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Power plays </p>
    
    <p>Your article about 2012&rsquo;s &ldquo;Parliamentarians of the year&rdquo; (National, Dec. 3) ignores the malaise of Parliament and the diminishing of democracy, as pointed out regularly by your political commentators such as Paul Wells. Question period is a circus. The PMO&rsquo;s control over elected members seems absolute. Harper&rsquo;s fist is a shadow everywhere. Your accounts only hint at the trouble.  </p>
    
    <p><em>Adrian Peetoom, Edmonton   </em></p>
    
     
    
    <p>One has to wonder how a radio talk-show host such as Calgary&rsquo;s Dave Rutherford, noted for mollycoddling right-of-centre guests while barely allowing Liberal or NDP guests the ability to finish a sentence without interruption, could possibly qualify for nomination as one of &ldquo;The 25 most important people in Ottawa&rdquo; (National, Dec. 3). Sorry, but even as a proud Albertan, and as bright as Dave Rutherford is, I can&rsquo;t see him in the company of Stephen Harper, Jason Kenney, Thomas Mulcair, et al. </p>
    
    <p><em>Marian Burke, Calgary </em></p>
    
    <p>It&rsquo;s happening here </p>
    
    <p>Your cover headline asked, &ldquo;Is Egypt becoming the next Iran?&rdquo; (Nov. 26), when a better question might be, &ldquo;Could Egypt become the next Canada?&rdquo; A religious, right-wing party that triumphs over a larger but more divided left has a familiar ring. If Egypt follows Canada&rsquo;s script, look for Mohamed Morsi to begin to solidify his control over the apolitical organs of state and maintain an obsessive distrust of the free press. Perhaps it&rsquo;s only a matter of time before we read of a fire sale of Egypt&rsquo;s greatest treasures, the pyramids, to the Chinese. Writer Michael Petrou offers solace to disillusioned voters in both countries when he notes, &ldquo;Courage alone won&rsquo;t help the liberals triumph at the ballot box. They are weak and divided. If they want to find a way back to political influence, they must unite.&rdquo; On that, we are all brothers. </p>
    
    <p><em>Mike Ward, Duncan, B.C. </em></p>
    
    <p>The drugs don&rsquo;t work </p>
    
    <p>Anne Kingston has done an excellent job of exposing Health Canada&rsquo;s failure to protect its citizens (&ldquo; &lsquo;A national embarrassment,&rsquo; &rdquo; National, Nov. 26). Allowing &ldquo;10,000-plus Canadians to die each year from a prescription drug taken exactly as prescribed&rdquo; is a scandal even if this were not &ldquo;likely a gross understatement.&rdquo; She mentions Dr. David Healy&rsquo;s book, <em>Pharmageddon</em>, but not the fact that earlier this year he launched a website (<em>RxISK.org</em>) to monitor information about side effects that the FDA, Health Canada and other regulators have ignored. Unlike the regulators, Healy&rsquo;s team reviews every report that comes in and provides immediate feedback to patients. Health Canada should be ensuring drugs are safe before allowing them to be prescribed to Canadians. I hope MP Terence Young succeeds in getting a drug safety agency to make this happen. </p>
    
    <p><em>Julie Wood, Toronto </em></p>
    
   
    
    <p>My hat is off to Terence Young for his efforts to bring the pharmaceutical industry to heel. There is no doubt in my mind that they put enormous pressure on doctors, hospitals and nurses to prescribe (and in some cases over-prescribe) their drugs. Young makes it clear that Canadians are not being protected by Health Canada against unscrupulous companies and their often dangerous drugs. </p>
    
    <p><em>Del Horn, Nanaimo, B.C. </em></p>
    
     
    
    <p>Yet again government has failed to act in the interests of the Canadian people, choosing, in this case, to act on behalf of multinational pharmaceutical corporations. The information in this article is shocking and should be shouted across the country. </p>
    
    <p><em>Bonnie Jesten, Kamloops, B.C. </em></p>
    
     
    
    <p>Regarding drugs and their safety, how about legislating that the trial participants can only be pharmaceutical industry executives and their direct families? That should improve the quality of the product. </p>
    
    <p><em>Graham Tarling, Victoria </em></p>
    
    <p>New World Vikings </p>
    
    <p>I appreciate <em>Maclean&rsquo;s</em> interest in my archaeological project related to a Norse presence in Arctic Canada (&ldquo;A twist in time,&rdquo; National, Nov. 26). However, the quoted comments from William Fitzhugh, of the Smithsonian Institution&rsquo;s Arctic studies centre, are both inaccurate and unfair in taking me to task for relying on insufficient evidence and in not publishing &ldquo;responsibly&rdquo; in the scientific literature. I have published on this subject as early as 2000, and in a 2006 conference paper presented evidence that these early dates were partly the result of chemical contamination. It should not be surprising that we have found new evidence of a Norse presence in the eastern Arctic, given the fact that a small nation of seafarers and hunters existed for over four centuries in Greenland, only two days&rsquo; sail from Baffin Island. Yet the topic of New World &ldquo;Vikings&rdquo; seems to not only generate automatic controversy among archaeologists, but to bring out their most competitive instincts.  </p>
    
    <p><em>Patricia Sutherland, University of Aberdeen, Scotland </em></p>
    
     
    
    <p>CORRECTION </p>
    
    <p>In the article &ldquo;The restaurants that matter&rdquo; (Power List, Dec. 3), auditor general Michael Ferguson was described as eating at Beckta Dining &amp; Wine. Ferguson has never been to that restaurant. <em>Maclean&rsquo;s</em> regrets the error.</p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>This week</sections>
    
    <body.head>
    
  <hedline>Good News</hedline>
  
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_WEEK_GOOD01.jpg"></photo>
 
    <photo.caption>Jean-Philippe Leguellec gets Canada&rsquo;s first World Cup biathlon victory</photo.caption>
    
 
    
  <photo.byline>Scanpix Sweden/Reuters</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>We&rsquo;re not alone </p>
    
    <p>NASA announced that its Messenger mission to Mercury has confirmed the existence of ice in deep, perpetually shaded craters at the poles of the planet nearest the sun. Neutron spectroscopy established the existence of hydrogen-rich deposits that must be water, but perhaps more interesting are signs that Mercury possesses chemically organic material: molecules containing carbon, captured from comets and asteroids. That could provide a crucial data point for measuring the extraterrestrial incidence of chemical preconditions for life.  </p>
    
    <p>A line in the ocean </p>
    
    <p>The Canada-Denmark doomsday clock inched backward from midnight as the countries reached formal agreement on a maritime boundary between Canada&rsquo;s Arctic possessions and self-governing Greenland. &ldquo;Denmark and Canada are showing that we can settle our disputes peacefully,&rdquo; said Denmark&rsquo;s foreign minister, Villy S&oslash;vndal. &ldquo;One might wish the same for the rest of the world.&rdquo; But keep your powder dry: the status of disputed Hans Island, lying athwart the sea boundary, awaits disposition.  </p>
    
    <p>Nice shot </p>
    
    <p>The twin governing bodies of golf inaugurated a 90-day &ldquo;comment period&rdquo; on a rule outlawing the use of &ldquo;belly putters&rdquo; anchored to the abdomen. &ldquo;I would stress this is not a popularity contest,&rdquo; said Peter Dawson of Scotland&rsquo;s Royal &amp; Ancient Golf Club of St. Andrews, which publishes the Rules of Golf along with the U.S. Golf Association. Both bodies believe a putter should swing freely like any other club; sports that succumbed to mechanical innovations like composite tennis rackets and hockey sticks might do well to follow golf&rsquo;s conservative example. </p>
    
    <p>Natural-born leader  </p>
    
    <p>U.S. Senator-elect Ted Cruz continued to develop presidential buzz last week, calling for Republicans to transcend class war and advocate a conservatism that emphasizes social mobility. Cruz was born in Calgary in 1970 to an oilman father, and the Constitution requires the President to be a &ldquo;natural-born citizen.&rdquo; Cruz has told the <em>New Yorker</em> he believes he qualifies. And why not? The U.S. has had good luck with chiefs born in British North America&mdash;i.e., the first seven presidents.</p>
    
<p>BAD NEWS</p>

    <p>Alarming agenda  </p>
    
    <p>A deputy in Hungary&rsquo;s National Assembly called for a &ldquo;tally&rdquo; of Jewish citizens, reviving old fears in a country hit hard by the Holocaust. M&aacute;rton Gy&ouml;ngy&ouml;si, foreign affairs critic for the nationalist Jobbik party, said fighting between Israel and Gaza &ldquo;makes it timely to count people of Jewish ancestry who live here,&rdquo; adding that Jews in government were a &ldquo;national security risk.&rdquo; Jobbik, which advocates an expanded &ldquo;Greater&rdquo; Hungary, drew one-sixth of the votes in the most recent national election.   Out for a pound  Figures from Her Majesty&rsquo;s Revenue and Customs revealed that the number of U.K. taxpayers declaring annual income of &pound;1 million fell from 16,000 to 6,000 last year in response to a new 50 per cent top tax bracket. Conservatives in the coalition government said the rate cost more than it raised, driving rich taxpayers out of Britain; opponents said the one-year change was caused by payments being shifted forward. Whatever the details, though, the tax was evaded with ease&mdash;a reminder that high marginal-tax rates are no budget panacea.  </p>
    

    <p>Un-intelligence  </p>
    
    <p>The espionage case involving former Canadian naval intelligence of&#64257;cer Jeffrey Delisle took yet another embarrassing turn. New documents show the RCMP only uncovered that Delisle was leaking secret files to Russia after being tipped off by American investigators. There were also reports this week that Canadian of&#64257;cials deleted important intelligence documents while reviewing an access-to-information request related to the Delisle case. Canada&rsquo;s security measures, it seems, still leave much to be desired. </p>
    
    <p>Religion and politics  </p>
    
    <p>The struggle in Egypt between Islamists and liberals intensified as supporters of Muslim Brotherhood-backed President Mohammed Morsi blockaded the nation&rsquo;s Supreme Court. Secularists and Christians had boycotted the creation of a new constitution, leading the Brotherhood-dominated constituent assembly to adopt a draft that would give Sunni clerics a legislative role and extend religious freedom only to &ldquo;Abrahamic faiths.&rdquo; The situation threatens to degenerate into a war between the judiciary and the country&rsquo;s Islamist mainstream.</p>
     
    
 </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
 <sections>This Week</sections>
 
  <body.head>
  
    <hedline>Newsmakers</hedline>
    
    <abstract>More exits from Montreal&rsquo;s political stage, the Pope tweets, and hockey  fans finally catch a break</abstract>
    
          <byline>Jaime J. Weinman, Kate Lunau and Aaron Wherry</byline>

  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_NEWSMAKERS99.jpg"></photo>
 
    <photo.caption>Benedict XVI</photo.caption>
 
  <photo.byline>Ramin Talaie/Bloomberg/Getty Images</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>On the side of Angels </p>
    
    <p>Ontario Judge Maureen Forestell may be the Hells Angels&rsquo; only friend on the bench. The Ontario judge ruled that a 2007 police raid had no right to seize their gold, diamonds, belt buckles and leather goods just because they had the Angels&rsquo; &ldquo;death head&rdquo; logo emblazoned on them. Forestell said the bling wasn&rsquo;t directly related to any crime sprees or attempts to intimidate people. In fact, she added, the club has a rule requiring its members to remove their merchandise &ldquo;when committing offences,&rdquo; and she ordered the swag returned to the bikers.  </p>
    
    <p>Too random an act of kindness? </p>
    
    <p>New York City cop Larry DePrimo became a seasonal hero last week when a photo of him giving a pair of boots and socks to a barefoot man on a frigid Manhattan night went viral. While the 25-year-old police of&#64257;cer was instantly beloved&mdash;and earned an invite to the <em>Today</em> show&mdash;it took New York&rsquo;s media a few days to track down the man with the new boots. When they did, the story grew a lot more complicated. Jeffrey Hillman isn&rsquo;t homeless, as he appeared to be. The deeply troubled Army vet has an apartment paid for by a benefit for homeless veterans. It also turns out Hillman is still barefoot. He told reporters that although he appreciated the cop&rsquo;s gesture, &ldquo;I could lose my life&rdquo; for wearing the $100 Skechers boots on the street. </p>
    
    <p>Your ticket to Mars </p>
    
    <p>This year, Internet billionaire Elon Musk&rsquo;s SpaceX, a private firm that builds spaceships, docked its Dragon spacecraft twice with the International Space Station&mdash;a first for a private company. Musk has bigger ambitions: he wants to put a human colony on Mars. Speaking at the Royal Aeronautical Society in London last week, the co-founder of PayPal and Tesla Motors said he&rsquo;d build a colony of 80,000 people willing to shell out $500,000 for a ticket, the price of a middle-class home in Toronto. No word yet on a timeline, but the 41-year-old has said he&rsquo;d like to retire on Mars, so he can&rsquo;t put it off too long.  </p>
    
    <p>Good news, bad news, hockey fans </p>
    
    <p>Canada&rsquo;s world junior team could end up benefiting from a little star power if the NHL lockout persists over Christmas. Headlining this year&rsquo;s selection camp roster is Ryan Nugent-Hopkins, the Edmonton Oilers star who tallied 18 goals and 34 assists in the NHL last season. The 19-year-old would surely help Canada in its quest to win a gold for the first time since 2009 and add to a tournament that will be like manna from heaven for the game&rsquo;s hockey-starved fans. But even in their time of need, the devotion of Canadian fans will be tested&mdash;Team Canada&rsquo;s &#64257;rst three games are due to be broadcast live from Russia at 4:30 a.m. EST. </p>
    
    <p>C U 2nite, Winnie? </p>
    
    <p>Who was the first giggling schoolgirl to get a message with the acronym &ldquo;OMG&rdquo;? Winston Churchill, it emerged this week. Its first known use was not in a text message or an email, but in a 1917 letter from the British admiral Lord Fisher to Churchill. Taking time out from the war, Fisher mentioned a rumour of a possible knighthood, adding &ldquo;O.M.G. (Oh! My God!).&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>The Zucker touch </p>
    
    <p>Few among us are able to land fantastic, high-profile jobs no matter how badly the last one went. The exception being Jeff Zucker. Last week, the former NBC president&mdash;famous for taking the network from &#64257;rst to fourth place, and for disastrous ideas like giving Jay Leno a prime-time show&mdash;was named the new head of CNN Worldwide, the struggling news channel. Zucker, a former producer of the <em>Today  </em>show, isn&rsquo;t promising a turnaround: ratings are &ldquo;not what defines the health of this business,&rdquo; he said last week after accepting the job. He should know. </p>
    
    <p>Holy tweeter </p>
    
    <p>On Monday, Pope Benedict XVI joined Twitter. By day&rsquo;s end, he&rsquo;d racked up almost a quarter of a million followers&mdash;without having issued a single tweet. &ldquo;The Pope is not the type of person who is checking his iPad or BlackBerry at meetings, so the tweets aren&rsquo;t going to be spontaneous like those from most other Twitter users,&rdquo; said the Holy See&rsquo;s media advisor, Greg Burke.  @Pontifex, who is expected to send his first tweet next week, will be dispensing &ldquo;pearls of wisdom&rdquo; in eight languages, he added. More exits in Quebec Montreal&rsquo;s political landscape is undergoing a seismic change as politicians depart, one after the other. Since the high-profile resignations of G&eacute;rald Tremblay and Gilles Vaillancourt, the mayors of Montreal and Laval, two more mayors have announced their resignations. Richard Marcotte, the mayor of Mascouche, a suburb just north of Montreal, resigned this week, seven months after his arrest on charges of fraud, corruption and conspiracy. Marcotte, who denies the charges, is alleged to have received &ldquo;benefits&rdquo; in return for municipal contracts. Meanwhile Claude  Trudel, the 70-year-old mayor of the Montreal borough of Verdun and a staunch Tremblay supporter, stepped down this week. Calling himself &ldquo;shaken&rdquo; by the departure of Montreal&rsquo;s long-time mayor, who resigned amid a corruption scandal, Trudel rejected playing a role in the coalition formed by Montreal&rsquo;s interim mayor, Michael Applebaum.  </p>
    
    <p>A doggone shame </p>
    
    <p>Who will stand up for dogs&rsquo; rights? New Toronto Blue Jays pitcher Mark Buehrle, that&rsquo;s who. The former Marlin&mdash;and long-time pit bull owner&mdash;clashed with Miami&rsquo;s ban on the dogs, but had the option to live in another county. Since the dogs are banned throughout Ontario, Buehrle is considering moving his family to New York state and making a daily two-hour commute to the Rogers Centre. Buehrle, who describes his pit bull as &ldquo;so loving and so awesome,&rdquo; complains the law is &ldquo;discriminatory,&rdquo; based on nothing but &ldquo;the way a dog looks.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Trading one jail for another </p>
    
    <p>A B.C. woman involved in what American authorities call the &ldquo;largest eco-terrorism case in United States history&rdquo; turned herself in last week after more than a decade on the run. Rebecca Rubin, 39, is facing charges in three states, including arson, conspiracy and use of a destructive device, relating to firebombing wild horse corrals in Oregon and California and a fire at a Colorado ski resort. Rubin &ldquo;was tired of life passing her by,&rdquo; said her lawyer, Ian Donaldson. &ldquo;She had been living in a prison without walls.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Mercy </p>
    
    <p>Last spring, the bodies of 54 sled dogs were pulled from a mass grave near Whistler, B.C. Robert Fawcett, a former part-owner of Howling Dog Tours, pleaded guilty in connection with the deaths of nine, saying the cull was necessary after a post-Olympics slump in sales. But his actions haunt him to this day, he revealed in a statement delivered at his sentencing hearing last week. Fawcett, who received death threats after news of the killings broke, suffered a nervous breakdown and was sent to a mental-health facility. The judge stopped short of giving him jail time, handing him three years&rsquo; probation, 200 hours of community service and a $1,500 fine. Fawcett still has nightmares about killing the dogs. &ldquo;I will never stop feeling guilty for the suffering that those dogs endured that day,&rdquo; he said through his lawyer. &ldquo;I feel like a part of me died with those dogs.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Fieri in Hogtown  </p>
    
    <p>Guy Fieri, the Food Network star with famously frosted tips, was spotted in Toronto filming <em>Diners, Drive-Ins and Dives</em> this week. Rumours put him at local greasy spoon landmarks like the Lakeview, Caplansky&rsquo;s Deli and Hey Meatball. Fieri&rsquo;s tour was capped off by a cooking session with Toronto rapper Drake. The bombastic chef seems to have recovered from a deliciously nasty review of his restaurant, Guy&rsquo;s American Kitchen &amp; Bar, in which <em>New York Times</em> critic Pete Wells wrote: &ldquo;When you hung that sign by the entrance that says, WELCOME TO FLAVOR TOWN!, were you just messing with our heads?&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>What was that about &lsquo;filth&rsquo;? </p>
    
    <p>Angus T. Jones is no Charlie Sheen. But the <em>Two and a Half Men</em> co-star seemed to be next in line to get fired when a video of him denouncing his popular sitcom as &ldquo;filth&rdquo; and urging viewers to tune out went viral last week. But fans paid him no attention, and Jones backed down, quickly issuing an abashed public apology. Unlike Sheen, who soon got another show, Jones is totally expendable: he wasn&rsquo;t even scheduled to appear in the two episodes following the outburst, and rumours have it that producers are considering replacing him with popular guest star Miley Cyrus. </p>
    
 
    <p>I&rsquo;ll text it to you&mdash;what&rsquo;s your number? </p>
    
    <p>It&rsquo;s gratifying to know that even Oscar-winning actress Meryl Streep couldn&rsquo;t resist taking an iPhone selfie with Hillary Clinton. The pair were attending the Kennedy Center Honors dinner, held at the U.S. State Department in Washington last weekend.</p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Opinion</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Thrown to the lions</hedline>
    
      <byline>Barbara Amiel</byline>

  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_AMIEL01.jpg"></photo>
 
    <photo.caption>Pariah: Protesters in Gaza after Canada was one of the few to vote against Palestinian statehood</photo.caption>
 
    
  <photo.byline>Mohamad Torokman/Reuters</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>It is a source of great historical anguish, in the United Nations, that the dreaded and odious Israel was formed as a result of a UN resolution. Accordingly it&rsquo;s necessary to establish that the UN was then under the domination of the U.S., the U.S.&nbsp;under the domination of Harry Truman, and Harry Truman under the domination of American Jews. I wish I had assembled those thoughts but they were William F. Buckley&rsquo;s in his 1974 book <em>United Nations Journal: A Delegate&rsquo;s Odyssey,</em> after his year as a U.S. delegate. I would not call Buckley a natural Judeo-phile but he had a strong moral sensibility and saw through cant and hypocrisy.  </p>
    
    <p>He would have recognized the farce at the UN last week and approved of the principled position Canada&rsquo;s government took. Foreign Affairs Minister John Baird is not really, whatever one&rsquo;s taste, a classic pin-up. But stay my beating heart. His speech to the UN on the proposal to advance Palestinian status (substituting negotiation with Israel for a love-in with the UN&rsquo;s non-aligned bloc) began: &ldquo;Canada opposes this resolution in the strongest terms . . . &rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>I expected thunder and a shaft of light from the heavens. No one in the UN ever opposes anything in &ldquo;the strongest terms&rdquo; apart from numbing condemnations of Israel&rsquo;s brutal, racist ethnic cleansing and occupation, beside which the brutal, racist ethnic cleansing of Africa and murderous wars of the Arab world fall mild as soft summer rains.&nbsp; </p>
    
    <p>True, Baird&rsquo;s speech went downhill as he carefully referenced resolution after resolution&mdash;181, 194, 242, 338, 1397, 1515, 1850 plus articles&mdash;but you know the Canadian way, all the &ldquo;i&rsquo;s&rdquo; dotted. Still, it was extraordinary. There really are politicians who swim against the tide because they think it morally right. </p>
    
    <p>Meanwhile, the CBC was happily announcing that 87 per cent of Canadians opposed Canada&rsquo;s No vote on the resolution to make the Palestinian Authority a non-member observer state of the UN. &ldquo;Let us know what you think by Twitter or email,&rdquo; said Peter Mansbridge, whom I forgive since this must be CBC policy. &ldquo;Think&rdquo; is the wrong word to use for 140-character hip-shooting.  </p>
    
    <p>Admittance to the UN club is rather like Aeroplan: collect status miles, or in this case, voting blocs to get into the next tier. To win, the Palestinians got the so-called &ldquo;non-aligned movement&rdquo; bloc of 120 votes which overlaps with the African Union (54 members) and the Arab League (22 members), all aligned by their dislike of the U.S. and Israel. This was topped up by the European Union bloc who voted for or abstained, apart from the No vote of Czech Republic&mdash;not coincidentally the least anti-Semitic country in Hitler&rsquo;s occupied Europe. The EU vote was largely strategic voting: you&rsquo;re a wannabe Security Council member? Okay. Vote against Israel and you&rsquo;ll get the non-aligned movement vote. </p>
    
    <p>One could cavil and say why believe the CBC&rsquo;s 87 per cent unscientific poll, but I do. Should Kiribati have membership at the UN? Poll Canadians and I&rsquo;ll bet 87 per cent say &ldquo;yes,&rdquo; not knowing it&rsquo;s had membership since 1999 and is about to become the first state with &ldquo;submerged&rdquo; status (its islands are going underwater due to the rising Pacific Ocean). This does make one wonder if Kiribati, population 104,000 and swimming, should have the same clout as Canada? And is it fair that Taiwan, population 23 million, which according to <em>The Economist</em> overtook Japan in GDP per capita in 2010, got heaved from the UN in 1971 at the behest of the Chinese Communists and is reduced to trying to enter UN organizations as a &ldquo;fishing entity&rdquo;? That 87 per cent doesn&rsquo;t represent informed public opinion so much as vagaries blowin&rsquo; in the wind.  </p>
    
    <p>What&rsquo;s blowing is a distinct lack of sympathy for the world&rsquo;s only Jewish state inconveniently situated amidst a witches&rsquo; brew of Arab states: Syria (Iran&rsquo;s proxy), Lebanon (home of the terrorist Hezbollah organization), Egypt (the Muslim Brotherhood) and Palestine, divided between rule by terrorist group Hamas and &ldquo;President&rdquo; Mahmoud Abbas, whose actual term as president ran out in 2009. He is also known as Abu Mazen, PLO supporter of the Munich Olympics massacre and schooled in the Soviet Union&rsquo;s Peoples&rsquo; Friendship University where his thesis was &ldquo;The connection between the Nazis and the leaders of the Zionist movement.&rdquo; Well, we all get heady when young. It&rsquo;s a toss-up which Arab state dislikes the Palestinians more: Jordan, which expelled the PLO in 1970 and massacred them; or Egypt, who till recently spent its efforts trying to keep Gaza&rsquo;s Palestinians out. If Israel disappeared, the Middle East would continue in much the same mess. This requires understanding of the Arab and Islamic world&rsquo;s divisions, which can be summed up by saying that Sunnis and Shias plus sects such as the Syrian Alawites kill each other and apostates all over the Muslim world with a savagery incomprehensible to the Western mind so Western minds do not focus on it. </p>
    
    <p>Israel can freeze settlements and give back land but unless all adults march into the sea sans lifebelts nothing will satisfy the Palestinians who steadfastly refused to recognize Israel as a Jewish state. What Abbas did in his UN speech was endorse Resolution 194, which provides for two states but allows the right of return to Israel of Arab &ldquo;refugees,&rdquo; a demographic bomb to eliminate a Jewish Israel. Abbas&mdash;an uncharismatic figure if ever there was one&mdash;couldn&rsquo;t bring himself to actually say two states for two peoples let alone mention that smelly word &ldquo;Jewish.&rdquo; It&rsquo;s easy enough to endorse a state called Israel, but when your intent is to make it the Islamic Republic of Israel (or possibly the Islamic State of the Children of Abraham, given the unction about Judaism and Islam being descended from Abraham) you enter the UN&rsquo;s Roman Colosseum and throw Jews to unaligned lions. The outcome is nothing to cheer about, unless you are a jackal, waiting for scraps.&nbsp;</p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Interview</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>On wildlife culls, engineering the landscape, and our misguided soft spot for Bambi</hedline>

     <abstract>Ken MacQueen in conversation with Jim Sterba</abstract>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_INTERVIEW03.jpg"></photo>
  <photo.byline>PHOTOGRAPHs BY STEPHANIE NORITZ</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Jim Sterba is a veteran foreign reporter at the <em>Wall Street Journal</em> and one-time war correspondent, but his latest book, <em>Nature Wars</em>, is about insurgency of a different sort: the resurgent population of North American wildlife and the uneasy relationship with its neighbours. Both humans and overabundant populations of deer, bear, goose, beaver, coyote and others have taken to suburban life with sometimes disastrous consequences. &ldquo;We turned a wildlife comeback miracle into a mess&rdquo; of fouled parks, deer-vehicle accidents and downed jetliners, he writes. He argues our Disneyfied view of animals has tipped the balance of nature. </p>
    
    <p>Q: I live in British Columbia, where trees are sacred and we love our wildwood creatures. Each has their own special interest group. Yet you say we have too much wildlife. </p>
    
    <p>A: Certain species are over-abundant, like white-tail deer in many parts of the country. Some are just nuisances, like Canada geese. Some are damaging, like beavers. The problem with bears is that people have such an anthropomorphized view of them because they haven&rsquo;t been around bears a lot, except teddy bears, so when a bear shows up they think, &ldquo;Oh, it&rsquo;s a cute little person,&rdquo; and they throw it a doughnut, or they let it rifle through the garbage can and take its photograph, and the bear begins to associate the smell of people with food, not fear. It&rsquo;s not the bear&rsquo;s fault, it&rsquo;s our fault. </p>
    
    <p>Q: We love our wildlife in theory, but in practice we don&rsquo;t understand it very much, do we? </p>
    
    <p>A: The last third of the book talks about how over the generations we&rsquo;ve become detached from nature, kind of de-natured in that we&rsquo;re not out on the working landscape anymore. In the 19th century, two out of three members of the workforce were working outdoors on farms. Now it&rsquo;s less than one per cent. We spend 90 per cent of our time indoors, in our cars, offices or homes. We&rsquo;ve been getting our nature as we moved off the landscape, the working landscape, indirectly from books, from movies, from TV, now digital images. </p>
    
    <p>Q: So it&rsquo;s all Walt Disney&rsquo;s fault? </p>
    
    <p>A: Long before Disney there were all these anthropomorphized creatures in films. The guys who sold the films said, &ldquo;We&rsquo;re interested in sales, not realism,&rdquo; so they created all this stuff that is laughable now. Then Walt Disney came along. <em>Bambi</em> is this anti-hunting classic, but it also reinforces the notion that when man goes out into nature, nature loses. Man is the bad guy. Man is not the ecosystem manager that he should be. That may be true, but there are still situations where we as a keystone species need to do some things for the health of the ecosystems we live in, for the good of the plants, animals and the people who live in it.  </p>
    
    <p>Q: You talk about how hunting, for deer especially, is so heavily regulated, and I would say in Canada hunters are practically social pariahs. And yet in the U.S. there was an astonishing figure in your book: there are 3,000 to 4,000 deer vehicle collisions a day. </p>
    
    <p>A: It&rsquo;s not only deer. There are millions upon millions of creatures, birds and small animals that we run over and we don&rsquo;t think about it except as a kind of ghoulish joke, roadkill. I talk about Canada&rsquo;s [wildlife] underpasses and overpasses to try to reduce that carnage on the roadways, but that&rsquo;s an amazing toll. The thing about deer car crashes&mdash;and worse, moose car crashes&mdash;is that virtually all those deer die, and upwards of 250 people die and 30,000 get hospitalized [a year]. There&rsquo;s something called a social-caring-capacity tipping point, beyond which the good of the animal begins to be outweighed by the problems it&rsquo;s causing in the minds of the people who are having to deal with it. </p>
    
    <p>Q: In Interior British Columbia the deer have become so bold that they are wandering around communities and attacking dogs, even people. There was a movement to cull deer, but then something called the Inverness Deer Protection Society launched a lawsuit. Among other things it seeks damages because a deer cull was causing members of the society mental anguish. </p>
    
    <p>A: The same thing is happening now in Rock Creek Park in Washington, D.C. There are so many deer they&rsquo;re completely eating away the plants and shrubs&mdash;three times more deer than the foliage can stand. They put together a 600-page environmental impact statement. Must have cost millions. Took 10 years. They were on the verge of culling the herd this winter when a California-based animal rights group&mdash;California has no white-tail deer&mdash;sued on behalf of about five Washington residents who said they would suffer irreparable mental anguish if the deer cull went on. People divide up into what I call species partisans. </p>
    
    <p>Q: Species partisans are generally defending deer, wolves, beavers or baby seals&mdash;generally the cute or noble beasts. I&rsquo;m not seeing a big pro-rat lobby out there. </p>
    
    <p>A: What animal protection people say is that if you kill out your problem beavers or your geese or your deer, or if you move them or do anything to eliminate the problem, you&rsquo;re creating a vacuum effect into which new members of the same species are going to come. But studies that have been done into deer culls have found after six to eight years the deer population has not increased other than that the deer that are left have fawns. The logic of the vacuum effect is this: why pull the weeds in your garden? New ones are going to grow back. Why trap the rats in your basement? Because you&rsquo;re managing that landscape. On family farms, predators were controlled because they would damage the things you were trying to grow. Now the landscape is full of trees and people that don&rsquo;t manage. I&rsquo;m not saying we shouldn&rsquo;t have any wildlife around, I&rsquo;m just saying people ought to know the consequences of their little management regimes. We&rsquo;re already in the landscape and yet there are so many people who say, &ldquo;Leave nature alone. Nature will balance itself. Nature will solve its own problems.&rdquo;<em> </em>
    </p>
    
    <p>Q: The front page of Vancouver&rsquo;s Province newspaper today talks about the need to cull tens of thousands of snow geese, clustering in Richmond, decimating  playing fields and parks. It&rsquo;s also the location of Vancouver International Airport. There are consequences to geese overrunning airports. </p>
    
    <p>A: It took the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 10 years to change the rules on culling geese. They were fought all the way. It took U.S. Airways Flight 1549 about 90 seconds to cement the notion that maybe something ought to be done [after a collision with a flock of Canada geese disabled its engines]. Something that I think about every time I get on an airplane. </p>
    
    <p>Q: Thank God for the Hudson River. </p>
    
    <p>A: Exactly.  </p>
    
    <p>Q: I live a 15-minute drive from downtown Vancouver. I&rsquo;ve had a bear picnic on our front lawn, we&rsquo;ve had raccoons in our attic and this week I almost stepped on a skunk getting out of my car. Your book spoke to me. </p>
    
    <p>A: This is a problem of riches, a problem of success. Our patch of the planet is really blessed to have all of these trees and all these wild birds and animals. It&rsquo;s the result of things we did to get them, nurture them and keep them. Parts of the world would envy what we have. It&rsquo;s very likely in this part of the eastern United States, which contains 60 per cent of our forest and almost two-thirds of our population, we are living in closer proximity to more wild birds, animals and trees than anywhere on the planet at any time in history.  </p>
    
    <p>Q: There is a lot of greenery around your weekend home in rural New York state. Isn&rsquo;t dealing with wildlife the price of admission? </p>
    
    <p>A: Absolutely. If you don&rsquo;t have any problem with these critters, I think they&rsquo;re fun to have around. I gave up hunting when I went to college in Michigan about 40 years ago. Since I&rsquo;ve been coming up here I&rsquo;ve taken it up again. I think of myself not as a deer hunter but sort of an ecosystem manager. </p>
    
    <p>Q: If you follow the arc of wildlife population growth of past decades, where is it going? </p>
    
    <p>A: Maybe that&rsquo;s my next book. Sorry to cop out. There are some solutions. If you don&rsquo;t want to use phrases like killing or culling or any of these other euphemisms, you can use what my deer consultant calls &ldquo;human-directed mortality.&rdquo; We&rsquo;re a keystone species. Like beavers we can engineer our landscape for whatever we want. It depends on how badly you think the species that are overabundant are causing problems. If it&rsquo;s just a messy golf course, you might be able to tolerate geese. If your water well is flooded by a beaver and your water is contaminated, you may want to get rid of the beaver. </p>
    
    <p>Q: What is the reaction to your book. Is it considered heresy by some people?  </p>
    
    <p>A: I&rsquo;ve gotten [heat] from goose people in New York City who believe that killing geese is like the Holocaust. Tell that to Holocaust survivors and historians. I was trashed by a feral cat protector. In the book, I don&rsquo;t say I want to kill stuff, I just quote other people saying this is an option. At all the talks I give, everyone has a problem. Everyone has an opinion and has taken a side on the issue. I think this book is timely because everyone is sensitized to the issue. </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>National</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Wealth Asylum</hedline>
    
    <abstract>Targeted by gangs for their money, rich Mexicans are fleeing to Canada as refugees</abstract>
    
    <byline>Charlie Gillis</byline>
    
    </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_RICHMEXICANS01.jpg"></photo>
  <photo.caption>Threatened: When gangs targeted their children, the Balcortas fled to Calgary</photo.caption>
    
  <photo.byline>Chris Bolin</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
    <p>In Mexico, Daniel Balcorta had it good. Three cars, a house with a pool, lavish meals at Cancun&rsquo;s top restaurants&mdash;such were the perks of a successful realtor selling beachfront on the Yucatan coastline. A former professional soccer player, Balcorta had paired minor celebrity with a strong grasp of Internet commerce, and developed a thriving business catering to well-heeled snowbirds from the U.S. and Canada. &ldquo;I even had a private jet I&rsquo;d rent to fly around my clients viewing properties,&rdquo; says the 34-year-old ruefully. &ldquo;We lived a very comfortable life.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>One call to his cellphone would change that. It was Aug. 14, 2009, and the man with the raspy voice on the other end introduced himself as a representative of &ldquo;the Company&rdquo;&mdash;gangster-speak for Los Zetas, a notorious criminal cartel known throughout Mexico for drug trafficking and extortion. The time had come for Balcorta to pay, the man said, and the price was 500,000 pesos (about $50,000). &ldquo;You must have the wrong person,&rdquo; Balcorta responded, and he promptly hung up. </p>
    
    <p>But the man called back, and thus began a month-long nightmare during which the gangsters called Balcorta and his wife, Maria, no less than 10 times demanding they pay up or else. When the Balcortas stopped answering, the gangsters left voice mails threatening their lives and those of their children, aged 5 and 2. On Aug. 17, Maria took a call at the house in which a man told her the Zetas would kill Balcorta &ldquo;or a member of your family&rdquo; unless she persuaded her husband to co-operate. They complained to police&mdash;twice&mdash;but the calls kept coming. </p>
    
    <p>The tipping point came Aug. 30, when the family returned from the luxury mall at Plaza la Isla to find their gate ajar and their front door pried open. The contents of the house were untouched: &ldquo;We&rsquo;d left $200 on the table to pay some bills,&rdquo; Balcorta marvels. &ldquo;They didn&rsquo;t take it.&rdquo; But by then they&rsquo;d noticed strangers watching their house from vehicles parked on the street. When their call to police about the break-in went unanswered yet again, the Balcortas planned their escape. That day, they moved to a friend&rsquo;s house, and on Sept. 13, they boarded a plane for Calgary, where they claimed asylum under Canada&rsquo;s refugee protection laws. </p>
    
    <p>With their Louis Vuitton clothing and laptop computers, the Balcortas are not your stereotypical refugees. Rather, they typify a wave of asylum-seekers whose flight from their home country has been dubbed the &ldquo;Mexodus&rdquo;&mdash;a mass withdrawal of monied, skilled Mexicans whose wealth has made them targets for narco-gangs back home. In the last six years, there have been some 286,000 complaints of extortion in the country, while an estimated two million shakedowns go unreported each year, most of them done over throwaway cellphones.  </p>
    
    <p>Many victims initially applied for U.S. visas, under provisions admitting people willing and financially able to start new businesses. But as the gangs turned to extortion and kidnapping for income about four years ago, an increasing number began seeking asylum on the grounds that they are persecuted and in need of protection. In 2009, Canada&rsquo;s Immigration and Refugee Board (IRB) received an astounding 9,000 claims from Mexico&mdash;more than triple the number five years earlier, and a figure that prompted the federal government to slap a visa requirement on visitors (it achieved the desired effect: by 2011, only 763 sought asylum). </p>
    
    <p>The IRB doesn&rsquo;t track claimants by income, and its decisions remain private unless an applicant appeals to federal court. But the handful of cases in the public domain point to a disturbing pattern. Shortly before the Balcortas arrived, the board heard the story of Javier Castillo Mendoza, a former distributor of Hewlett-Packard office equipment who testified he received a series of demands for cash over the phone before he was kidnapped by corrupt police in August 2005. He was released, he said, after his wife delivered an $8,000 ransom to a local police station. After receiving another extortion demand in April 2007&mdash;this time for $25,000&mdash;he closed his business and fled to Toronto with his wife and four children. </p>
    
    <p>Mendoza&rsquo;s plight, in turn, closely resembled that of Alejandro Blando, a distributor of wireless network plans who in 2008 came under threats from men claiming links to Mexico&rsquo;s Federal Investigation Agency. In Blando&rsquo;s case, the callers didn&rsquo;t want money but undocumented phone lines through which&mdash;presumably&mdash;they could conduct illegal business. </p>
    
    <p>Such cases pose a dilemma for countries like Canada and the U.S., says Paul Rexton Kan, a professor at the U.S. Army War College who has studied Mexico&rsquo;s so-called &ldquo;narco-refugees.&rdquo; Giving safe haven to Mexico&rsquo;s skilled and wealthy flies in the face of the spirit of NAFTA, he notes, but the plain truth is their own government can&rsquo;t shield them. &ldquo;There&rsquo;s no such thing as witness protection in Mexico,&rdquo; says Kan from his office in Carlisle Barracks, Pa. &ldquo;Only five per cent of crimes get solved, and only two per cent result in conviction. You have the basic collapse of judicial and law enforcement systems.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>That sense of conflicting obligations has played out in Canada in cases where the IRB has been reluctant to extend asylum to wealthy Mexicans, and the federal court has told it to reconsider. In several cases, including Balcorta&rsquo;s, the IRB has concluded that monied Mexicans don&rsquo;t qualify for asylum because all Mexicans face gang crime, and the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act offers no protection against &ldquo;a risk faced generally by other individuals.&rdquo; The court, however, has held that a wealthy person singled out by the gangsters faces a very specific threat. &ldquo;The risks of those standing in the same vicinity of the gunman,&rdquo; wrote Justice Michel Shore in sending Balcorta&rsquo;s case back for another IRB hearing, &ldquo;cannot be considered the same as the risks of those standing directly in front of him.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>The stalemate is unlikely to last. Last week, Prime Minister Stephen Harper confirmed the government&rsquo;s plan to lift the visa requirement on Mexicans travelling to Canada&mdash;a move that could open the gates to another flood of asylum claims. To avoid that scenario, the feds are expected to add Mexico to Canada&rsquo;s list of &ldquo;designated safe countries,&rdquo; which would make it easier to deport refugees claimants after the IRB rejects them. Sharryn Aiken, an immigration law expert with Queen&rsquo;s University, believes that would be a mistake: &ldquo;If you look at the stats, you&rsquo;re going to see a significant percentage of well-founded claims from Mexico. The federal court has [examined] some of these IRB decisions, found that they got it wrong and sent them back.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>The Balcortas, meanwhile, have their second shot at refuge in an as-yet unscheduled IRB hearing. Their children&mdash;Carla, 8, Rodrigo, 4, and Santiago, 2&mdash;are &ldquo;Canadian through and through,&rdquo; Daniel says (unbeknownst to him, Maria was pregnant with their third when they fled Mexico). And though lack of immigration status has hampered his job searches, he&rsquo;s found work as a marketing consultant while coaching top-flight youth soccer teams in his spare time. To top it off, Balcorta was nominated last week for one of Calgary&rsquo;s coveted Immigrant of Distinction Awards&mdash;a gesture that reinforced his belief that one day those threatening phone calls will prove a blessing. &ldquo;Canada,&rdquo; he says, &ldquo;has moral values that other countries have lost.&rdquo;     </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>National</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Crime and the new punishment</hedline>
    
    <abstract>Even good students can  run into trouble with the law. Dalhousie is stepping in  with a kinder approach.</abstract>
    
    <byline>Andrew Stobo Sniderman</byline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_RESTORATIVE01.jpg"></photo>
     <photo.caption>Getting smart: The &lsquo;post-event crime prevention&rsquo; allows students to avoid fines or criminal records</photo.caption>
 
    
  <photo.byline>Peter Dench/GETTY IMAGES</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>University offers most students their first real taste of freedom from home and family, including the freedom to do stupid and illegal things. Even good students can become drunken criminals. </p>
    
    <p>This year, Dalhousie University unveiled a restorative justice program for students charged with relatively minor criminal offences. The university hopes to address crime without large fines or the prospect of a criminal record. It is Canada&rsquo;s most ambitious effort by a university to get involved in criminal justice for its students. Other schools seem less keen to follow. Should universities act when students commit crimes off campus? </p>
    
    <p>Fresh-faced undergraduates not infrequently find themselves teetering in a public place with open bottles of booze in front of unimpressed police of&#64257;cers. It happens.  Indeed, it happened to hundreds of students at Dalhousie University last year. Each received a &#64257;ne of $457.41. Those who were careless enough to damage property received the distinction of criminal records. </p>
    
    <p>The Dalhousie two-year pilot program, made possible by an agreement between the provincial government, the Halifax police and the university, allows students to avoid fines or criminal records altogether. To do so, they must meet with affected members of the community and fashion an appropriate remedy, typically some form of volunteer program. &ldquo;The program asks students to accept responsibility, gives victims a voice, creates a sense of community, and hopefully changes behaviour more than anonymously paying a ticket does,&rdquo; says Dianne Norman, Dalhousie&rsquo;s manager of student dispute resolution. The model was borrowed from a juvenile justice program in Nova Scotia for youth 17 and under that saw about 90 per cent compliance rates, its proponents hope it will eventually also apply to non-students across the province. </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;Students learn little by paying a fine,&rdquo; says Norman. &ldquo;They pay the ticket and they&rsquo;re done. They haven&rsquo;t learned anything except to do it without getting caught next time. Many pay from mom and dad&rsquo;s bank account.&rdquo; Since the fall semester began, more than 130 students have enrolled in the restorative justice program. Michael Burns, Dal&rsquo;s head of campus security, calls it &ldquo;post-event crime prevention.&rdquo; &ldquo;If we can reduce recurrence without applying the sanction of a criminal record, that&rsquo;s a good thing.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>The University of British Columbia takes a more hands-off approach. When some of its students faced prosecutions for partaking in the orgy of breaking and stealing in the aftermath of the Stanley Cup playoffs in 2011, the university took no disciplinary action. Punishing off-campus crime was not viewed as within the school&rsquo;s mandate, even with Vancouverites baying for punishment as the justice process raced along like a slug.    </p>
    
    <p>Fanshawe College took the opposite approach after last year&rsquo;s riots in London, Ont. Eight students were implicated in wanton destruction that left the community aghast. Howard Rundle, the school&rsquo;s president, promptly suspended the students while their criminal proceedings were still ongoing. Rundle argued that the school&rsquo;s code of conduct extended to egregious behaviour off campus. When schools such as Fanshawe discipline off-campus criminality, their students are guaranteed to be punished once and risk getting punished twice. </p>
    
    <p>The architect of Dalhousie&rsquo;s new program, law professor Jennifer Llewellyn, can understand why UBC opted not to get involved if the only option was additional punishment. As for Fanshawe College, she views its swift discipline as &ldquo;both too little and too much. Punitive measures are a blunt instrument. They don&rsquo;t really let us understand what went wrong and address it.&rdquo;  </p>
    
    <p>The issue extends beyond the misdeeds of students. &ldquo;The fear from the riots,&rdquo; Llewellyn says, &ldquo;was that civic trust in young people was breached. That&rsquo;s the real worry. No number of criminal prosecutions is going to adequately rebuild that social trust.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Perhaps Dalhousie will help its students learn better from their mistakes. The larger challenge remains. &ldquo; &lsquo;Town-gown&rsquo; tension is an age-old problem,&rdquo; Norman says. &ldquo;Maybe we&rsquo;ve been going about it in the wrong way. Maybe it&rsquo;s time to recognize the broader impact students have on their community rather than just focusing on the individuals getting caught.&rdquo;     </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>National</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>An unwelcome proposal</hedline>
    
  </body.head>
    
 
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_NATNOTES01.jpg"></photo>
 
    
  <photo.caption>Maritime premiers</photo.caption>
    
  <photo.byline>Photographs by Mitchel Raphael; Christinne Muschi/Reuters</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Stop us if you&rsquo;ve heard this one: by forming a Maritime union, the provinces of Prince Edward Island, New Brunswick and Nova Scotia will finally have the clout necessary to fix what ails them. When three Tory senators from the region suggested such a merger last week, it was the latest in a long line of failed attempts at provincial matrimony. With a backlash already under way, it&rsquo;s hard to see this proposal ending any differently. </p>
    
    <p>There&rsquo;s no question the provinces face huge problems. Unemployment is well above the national average, their populations are aging rapidly, and the region is increasingly dependent on federal support even as Ottawa grows stingy. Proponents of a union say a consolidated bureaucracy would be more cost-effective, and the provinces would not have to compete against each other for investment.  </p>
    
    <p>Similar arguments were made back in 1864, when politicians from the Maritime colonies met in Charlottetown to talk about forming a union, but their plans were derailed when Sir John A. Macdonald arrived with a plentiful supply of champagne and a rather larger proposal&mdash;the Dominion of Canada. A century later New Brunswick premier Louis Robichaud proposed an Atlantic Canada union (including Newfoundland). Observers thought he was joking. Then in the 1970s, with Quebec separatist sentiment rising, a union was eyed in case the struggling region found itself cut off. </p>
    
    <p>Canada&rsquo;s tiniest province is the most vocal opponent of this latest merger proposal, with P.E.I. Premier Rob Ghiz calling it &ldquo;preposterous.&rdquo; Still, P.E.I. had much the same response when Confederation was discussed in 1864. Nine years later, facing a debt crisis, the province reconsidered. Perhaps all the Maritime union needs is more time.</p>
    
     <byline>Mika Rekai</byline>



<p>A warlock scam and an unlucky ride</p>


    <p>British Columbia: A manager at the Red Lion Inn in Saanich faces five charges of aggravated assault after allegedly stabbing five employees with a pair of closed scissors at the hotel&rsquo;s Jade Fountain Restaurant. Police say the manager, 52-year-old Zhi Wei Meng, who goes by the name Wally, then locked himself in an office, where they arrested him. There were no fatalities. </p>
    
    <p>Alberta: A 32-year-old truck driver from Stettler was driving with a loaded rifle leaning against the passenger seat with the muzzle pointed at the roof. While making a U-turn, the rifle tipped over and went off. The bullet passed through the man&rsquo;s stomach and out the door. He is in stable condition, but faces charges for reckless use of a firearm. Saskatchewan: In late November police in northern Saskatchewan were called to investigate reports of a man driving a snowmobile while impaired, but the man went off-road and eluded them. The next day a 43-year-old snowmobiler, who police believe was the same man they were searching for, was found dead by his brother after his snowmobile crashed through the ice at Deschambault Lake.  </p>
    
  
    <p>Ontario: A Mississauga man who self-publishes a Spanish-language newspaper has been charged with fraud after a woman accused him of falsely posing as a spiritual healer and bilking her out of $14,000 for various spells. Gustavo Valencia Gomez, 40, a self-described warlock, allegedly convinced the 56-year-old woman her family was cursed and needed his services.  </p>
    
    <p>Newfoundland: The Mounties always get their man . . . eventually. An off-duty RCMP officer from Corner Brook was driving near Deer Lake when he picked up a hitchhiker.  When the hitchhiker introduced himself as Ken Colson, the officer realized the man was a fraud suspect he had been pursuing for six years. The officer, Const. Des Burridge, quietly pulled over, identified himself and arrested Colson.</p>
    
     <byline>Mika Rekai</byline>
  
    



   <p>Capital Diary: Mitchel Raphael on mo&rsquo; revelry and babysitting vampires</p>


    <p>Lanny McDonald, Tom Selleck and the NDP  </p>
    
    <p>The NDP held a facial-hair contest at their watering hole Brixton&rsquo;s to mark the end of Movember, the month-long campaign that uses moustaches to promote awareness of prostate cancer. NDP Leader Thomas Mulcair and MP Olivia Chow were the judges. The first category was the Jack Layton moustache. With so many young people in the NDP, Chow quipped that many were &ldquo;early Layton moustaches.&rdquo; In the end, the winner was Nova Scotia MP Robert Chisholm for his older version of the Layton &rsquo;stache. Most intimidating moustache, named after Calgary Flames Lanny McDonald, was a draw between MPs Fin Donnelly and Jean Rousseau. NDP staffer Fran&ccedil;ois Soucy took home the honour of raising the most money for prostate cancer and was given a DVD set of Magnum, P.I., starring moustache icon Tom Selleck. The &ldquo;Mo&rsquo; sister&rdquo; award went to MP Alexandrine Latendresse. Mulcair decided to create a new category on the spot, &ldquo;The best Colonel Sanders,&rdquo; which went to MP Malcolm Allen&rsquo;s white whiskers. Mulcair didn&rsquo;t opt for a moustache for Movember. He has had his beard since he was 18. He only shaved it all off once when he and his wife, Catherine Mulcair, went in costume for a performance of Grease&mdash;no one recognized him without a beard and wearing a leather biker jacket. Another time he shaved off everything but a moustache and again people did not recognize him. His wife said he needs to just keep the beard. </p>
    
    <p>Damn those McDonald&rsquo;s smoothies </p>
    
    <p>Joan Crockatt, the Conservative candidate who won the recent Calgary Centre by-election, was on the Hill last week for some orientation. She says that, as a former journalist, she is aware of some of the pitfalls of being a new politician, including the endless receptions where one can pack on the pounds. Toward the end of the campaign, she said, &ldquo;I couldn&rsquo;t understand why I wasn&rsquo;t losing weight door-knocking.&rdquo; Then she realized the problem. During the by-election, she developed an addiction to McDonald&rsquo;s smoothies&mdash;pomegranate, in particular. </p>
    
    <p>Diane Finley&rsquo;s guilty pleasure </p>
    
    <p>My Babysitter&rsquo;s a Vampire won this year&rsquo;s Shaw Rocket Prize of $50,000. The award recognizes the best in Canadian kids&rsquo; programming. On hand announcing the winner at the Fairmont Ch&acirc;teau Laurier was Minister of Human Resources and Skills Development Diane Finley. The minister said children&rsquo;s programs are one of her guilty pleasures. &ldquo;I&rsquo;m kind of addicted to Artzooka,&rdquo; said Finley of the program where, according to the show&rsquo;s website, host Jeremie Saunders &ldquo;shows you how to create masterpieces out of recycled materials and how to tackle original projects using tech gadgets.&rdquo;  </p>
    
    <p>Garneau shoots for the stars </p>
    
    <p>Canada&rsquo;s first astronaut in space, Marc Garneau, is the latest to join the Liberal leadership race. His campaign has already been peppered with space references and his website declares: &ldquo;Let&rsquo;s take Canada to new heights.&rdquo; Liberal insiders like the references and say Garneau should use what he&rsquo;s got. The approach is in contrast to that of former Liberal MP and hockey legend Ken Dryden, who opted not to use hockey references in his 2006 Liberal leadership race because he wanted to be taken more seriously. Dryden won six Stanley Cups over his hockey career. In other Liberal leadership news, front-runner Justin Trudeau may have an unfair advantage in the opposition lobby. The brand of mineral water served there is Saint Justin, which is sourced from the Quebec&rsquo;s lower Laurentian Mountains.</p>
     
     
     
     
       <p>Trudeau vs. the Tories, round two</p>

     
    <p>Last week, Conservative MP Blaine Calkins proposed that the standing committee on natural resources &ldquo;conduct hearings on the economic bene&#64257;ts that &#64258;ow from Alberta&rsquo;s energy sector across Canada.&rdquo; That much was rather innocuous, but Calkins attached a suggestion to it: &ldquo;that members of Parliament David McGuinty and Justin Trudeau be invited as witnesses to explain their comments.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Here, apparently, was an attempt to put McGuinty and Trudeau on trial for their recent newsworthy remarks about elected Albertans. (McGuinty told Alberta Tories to &ldquo;go home,&rdquo; while comments from Trudeau in 2010 surfaced in which he complained, &ldquo;Albertans control our community.&rdquo;) With Trudeau the frontrunner to win the Liberal leadership race, the idea must seem particularly tempting. But while the motion passed and Trudeau&rsquo;s spokeswoman says he will testify&mdash;sitting MPs can&rsquo;t be forced to appear&mdash;the Conservatives might be about to give Trudeau an opening to turn their attacks around. &ldquo;I bet Justin Trudeau can&rsquo;t believe his good fortune,&rdquo; Keith Beardsley, a former strategist in the Prime Minister&rsquo;s Office, wrote on his blog. &ldquo;Do the Conservatives believe voters won&rsquo;t see them as being vindictive and petty? Do they actually think they will win the media war when Trudeau testifies?&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>If or when Trudeau testifies&mdash;no date has been set&mdash;it will be a closely watched spectacle. But as much as Conservative committee members will have an opportunity to condemn and perhaps corner him with difficult questions, Trudeau will get to respond in kind or claim the high road and possibly, in the process, prove himself capable of duking it out. The last time Conservatives were eager to see Trudeau embarrassed on a public stage, Senator Patrick Brazeau ended up with a bloody nose and the discounted Liberal landed a TKO victory.</p>
    
     <byline>Aaron Wherry</byline>
 
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>International</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
 <hedline>Grover: not  over </hedline>
    
    <abstract>Grover Norquist&rsquo;s  anti-tax allies may be spooked by the fiscal cliff. But he&rsquo;s not done yet.</abstract>
    
    <byline>Luiza Ch. Savage</byline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_US01.jpg"></photo>
 
    <photo.caption>Showdown: Norquist (left) faces mutiny, with some Republicans publicly wishing him harm</photo.caption>
    
 
  <photo.byline>Tom Williams/GETTY IMAGES</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Long before the Tea Party movement&rsquo;s mass rallies or the ideological inquisitions of recent Republican primary races, there was the bearded and burly man from suburban Boston. </p>
    
    <p>In 1981, at the age of 25, Grover Norquist, armed with economics and business degrees from Harvard, came to Washington on a mission to help carry out the Reagan revolution and promote his passionate belief in smaller government. His weekly &ldquo;Wednesday meetings,&rdquo; held in a conference room at his Washington headquarters, regularly attracted conservative lawmakers, activists and commentators. And Americans for Tax Reform, the activist group he founded in 1985, has since become a permanent fixture of the political landscape. &ldquo;The government&rsquo;s power to control one&rsquo;s life derives from its power to tax,&rdquo; the group&rsquo;s mission statement reads. &ldquo;We believe that power should be minimized.&rdquo;  </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;I don&rsquo;t want to abolish government,&rdquo; Norquist explained in a 2001 radio interview, &ldquo;I simply want to reduce it to the size where I can drag it into the bathroom and drown it in the bathtub.&rdquo;  </p>
    
    <p>A key tool in his effort was the &ldquo;Taxpayer Protection Pledge,&rdquo; signed by almost all congressional Republicans. With it, lawmakers pledge to oppose &ldquo;any and all efforts&rdquo; to increase taxes, and promise that &ldquo;any&rdquo; reduction of deductions and credits be offset by lowering overall tax rates.  </p>
    
    <p>Now, President Barack Obama and congressional Republicans are racing to come up with a deal that would avert the $500-billion hit to the economy from the expiration of Bush-era tax cuts coupled with automatic spending reductions that are scheduled to kick in Jan. 1&mdash;sudden austerity that could send the economy back into recession. Obama, who won re-election campaigning on higher taxes for the rich, insists that they be included. But as they seek a mutually acceptable plan to wrestle with a budget deficit of $1.2 trillion this year and a $16-trillion debt&mdash;the equivalent of 100 per cent of U.S. GDP&mdash;the Republican &ldquo;no new taxes&rdquo; pledge is a straitjacket.  </p>
    
    <p>Yet according to Norquist, now 56, the pledge is irrevocable. &ldquo;It is considered binding as long as an individual holds the office for which he or she signed the pledge,&rdquo; his website states, pointing out that candidates were voted in on the basis of signing it. </p>
    
    <p>In the face of the showdown over the looming &ldquo;fiscal cliff,&rdquo; however, a handful of Republican lawmakers have begun to balk. And Democrats are waiting to see whether they are the exception or the first crack in the once-impenetrable wall that Norquist spent his career building.  </p>
    
    <p>House Speaker John Boehner has already said that Republicans would agree to raising $800 billion by closing some &ldquo;loopholes&rdquo; or tax deductions, a technical violation of the pledge. Some Republicans would even consider signing off on Obama&rsquo;s demand for higher tax rates on upper-income earners.  </p>
    
    <p>First came a Republican senator from Georgia: &ldquo;I care more about my country than I do about a 20-year-old pledge,&rdquo; Saxby Chambliss told a hometown TV station on Nov. 22. </p>
    
    <p>Next, South Carolina Republican Lindsey Graham delivered the same message. &ldquo;I will violate the pledge for the good of the country,&rdquo; said the senator. &ldquo;The only pledge we should be making to each other is to avoid being Greece.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Norquist shrugged off the threats as mere posturing. &ldquo;No pledge-taker has voted for a tax increase,&rdquo; he told CNN. &ldquo;We&rsquo;ve had some people discussing impure thoughts on national television.&rdquo; But the intra-Republican conversation quickly grew more heated. </p>
    
    <p>Peter King, a plain-spoken Republican congressman from New York, says he doesn&rsquo;t consider himself bound by Norquist either. &ldquo;A pledge you signed 20 years ago, 18 years ago, is for that Congress,&rdquo; he said. &ldquo;If I were in Congress in 1941, I would have supported a declaration of war against Japan. I&rsquo;m not going to attack Japan today.&rdquo; Norquist shot back that King was trying to &ldquo;weasel out&rdquo; of the pledge. &ldquo;I hope his wife understands that commitments last a little longer than two years,&rdquo; he said. </p>
    
    <p>King exploded, calling Norquist a &ldquo;low-life&rdquo; for bringing up his marriage. He&rsquo;d &ldquo;better hope he doesn&rsquo;t meet [my wife],&rdquo; he told Politico. &ldquo;She&rsquo;ll knock his head off.&rdquo; Apparently King was not the only Republican wishing physical harm on Norquist. </p>
    
    <p>Alan Simpson, an 81-year-old former Republican senator from Wyoming who was tasked by Obama with helping America find a way out of its fiscal problems&mdash;and who co-authored the Bowles-Simpson plan, which aimed to do just that&mdash;had a few choice words for Norquist, whom he called a &ldquo;zealot.&rdquo; &ldquo;So how do you deal with someone who comes to stop government?&rdquo; Simpson said. &ldquo;Grover wandering the earth in his white robe, saying he wants to drown government in the bathtub. I hope he slips in there with it.&rdquo;  </p>
    
    <p>But within days, things looked brighter for Norquist. On Thursday, Obama came out with his negotiating position: he proposed $1.6 trillion in tax increases (double what Boehner, the Republican Speaker, was offering), $50 billion in new spending and only $400 billion in spending cuts (Republicans want more than a trillion). Graham called it a &ldquo;joke.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>On Monday, Norquist told National Public Radio the proposal was so unappealing to Republicans that he didn&rsquo;t have to worry about anyone breaking their pledge to support it. &ldquo;The Obama administration,&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;has solved all my problems.&rdquo; At least for the moment.     </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>International</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Lessons from &lsquo;Lincoln&rsquo; </hedline>
    
    <abstract>Preston Manning on the new Spielberg film,  Lincoln&mdash;and what Obama could learn from it</abstract>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_LINCOLN01.jpg"></photo>
  <photo.caption>Reconciliation: Resolving the current crisis in the U.S. means embracing rivals, as Lincoln did</photo.caption>
    
  <photo.byline>Tom Williams/GETTY IMAGES</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
    <p>Lincoln, Steven Spielberg&rsquo;s new film, tells the story of a dramatic period in the life of Abraham Lincoln near the end of the American Civil War. It is the period between Lincoln&rsquo;s re-election to a second term as president of the United States on Nov. 8, 1864, and the passage, several months later, of the constitutional amendment that permanently abolished slavery throughout the U.S. </p>
    
    <p>President Barack Obama has been re-elected to his second term at a time when America is again seriously divided racially and politically&mdash;racked by what CNN commentator John King described on election night as &ldquo;an ideological civil war.&rdquo; This conflict currently prevents a divided U.S. government from averting the fiscal crisis that threatens to plunge the American economy into recession. </p>
    
    <p>So what were the principles and tactics employed by Lincoln to bring together a Congress divided over abolition? And how might they apply to bringing together a U.S. government divided over the fiscal issue and hasten the end of America&rsquo;s ideological civil war? </p>
    
    <p>
      <em>Bring rivals onside:</em> In her book Team of Rivals, Doris Kearns Goodwin describes how Lincoln included four of his most bitter political opponents in his war cabinet, rather than ignoring them or banishing them to the political wilderness. These included secretary of state William Seward, attorney general Edward Bates and secretary of the treasury Salmon Chase&mdash;three of Lincoln&rsquo;s competitors for the Republican presidential nomination in 1860. </p>
    
    <p>One wonders if the U.S. government would now be drawing back from the &ldquo;fiscal cliff&rdquo; if on election night Obama&rsquo;s acceptance speech had included something more Lincolnian, something more like this: &ldquo;Significant differences exist between myself and Mitt Romney, which have been bitterly debated during this campaign. But I am resolved that there should be a coming together of our two great parties on the serious fiscal issues that divide us and the country. In particular, there needs to be a coming together of myself and Congress to resolve the impasse over the changes in spending and taxation required to avert a financial crisis. To that end, I am inviting governor Romney to join with a prominent Democrat [Bill Clinton?] to head a reconciliation task force to find common ground for action by myself and the Congress on the fiscal issue before Jan. 1st, 2013.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>
      <em>Add humour:</em> Lincoln was famous for his storytelling abilities; most of his stories had a folksy, humorous dimension that made people laugh at themselves and the circumstances being described. Lincoln used this ability, not only in his public addresses, but with cabinet colleagues. He used humorous stories to diffuse tense impasses in Cabinet or to make a telling point in an inoffensive way. </p>
    
    <p>Lincoln&rsquo;s humour was disarming&mdash;so was his lack of pretentiousness. Known for his height, he would frequently break the ice with visitors to his office by challenging them to measure to see who was the tallest. And his slightly rumpled appearance, contrasted in the movie with the more polished and uptight appearance of his cabinet colleagues, also tended to set people at ease. </p>
    
    <p>By way of contrast, few candidates or elected of&#64257;cials today are genuine and humorous storytellers. The sarcasm, ridicule and vicious witticisms that characterize so much of today&rsquo;s political humour tend to heighten tensions between competing candidates and parties rather than diffuse them. And the carefully crafted and coiffed public images of today&rsquo;s candidates smack more of artificiality and pretense than of the down-to-earth genuineness required to inspire public confidence. </p>
    
    <p>
      <em>Build and shrewdly manage a temporary coalition:</em> The 13th amendment to the U.S. Constitution outlawed slavery and involuntary servitude throughout the U.S. To secure its passage, Lincoln had to secure the support of a reluctant House of Representatives. (The Senate had already passed the measure.) </p>
    
    <p>When elected chambers are asked to approve measures fraught with moral implications, invariably, three groups of people must be dealt with: those who will support the measure on principle, those who are opposed no matter what, and those in the &ldquo;mushy middle,&rdquo; who are conflicted or undecided. </p>
    
    <p>In Lincoln, the main focus is how Lincoln&mdash;through Seward and three unscrupulous lobbyists hired by him&mdash;manages to persuade 20 congressmen in the mushy middle to either abstain from the vote or reluctantly side with abolitionists. Some are bribed with offers of public office upon their departure from Congress. Others are bullied and threatened. The tactics are unprincipled and effective because the targets are unprincipled. </p>
    
    <p>But crucial to the amendment&rsquo;s passage is the conduct of one of the most principled members of the House, Thaddeus Stevens, a Pennsylvania Republican. If Stevens, in his zeal for abolition, pushes too hard, or tries to extend the principle of equality for all under the law to a declaration of the equality of blacks and whites in all respects, he will drive those in the mushy middle into the opposite camp. How Stevens is encouraged and restrained, without being alienated or hopelessly compromised, is one of the highlights of the movie. </p>
    
    <p>If the ideological civil war in the United States is to cease, or to be ameliorated, or at least to be suspended until the fiscal crisis is dealt with, a temporary coalition of Democrats and Republicans needs to be built and managed to that end.  </p>
    
    <p>
      <em>Know when to stop fighting:</em> One of the closing scenes of Spielberg&rsquo;s Lincoln is the dignified reception of the defeated Confederate general, Robert E. Lee, by the victorious Union general, Ulysses S. Grant, at Appomattox, Va.&mdash;an event which marked the official end of the U.S. Civil War. Lee&rsquo;s cameo appearance reminds us that in graciously accepting defeat, he played a major role in setting a bitterly divided country on the road to reunification. </p>
    
    <p>During the last few weeks of the war&mdash;when it was evident to Lee that the war was lost&mdash;Confederate president Jefferson Davis urged it be continued through guerrilla tactics. Had this occurred, vicious, localized guerrilla conflict might have continued to poison the relationship between the North and South for decades. To Lee&rsquo;s credit, he categorically rejected it. The time had come for peace and reconciliation. </p>
    
    <p>Cessation of the ideological civil war in the U.S. could be hastened if Obama initiated a reconciliation process in the spirit of Lincoln. But it could also be hastened if the Republicans, who lost the election, could, in the spirit of Lee, acknowledge that the war is over (at least for now), and resist the temptation to prolong the con&#64258;ict inde&#64257;nitely via the employment of guerrilla tactics in Congress. </p>
    
    <p>
      <em>Pursue reconciliation at its most profound level:</em> The final scene of Lincoln shows the president on the steps of the Capitol Building on March 4, 1865, delivering his second inaugural address. The speech is considered by many, myself included, to be Lincoln&rsquo;s &#64257;nest. One of its deepest insights is Lincoln&rsquo;s belief that reconciliation, at its most profound level, is as much spiritual as it is political. It is, by far, the most religious of all presidential inaugural addresses. </p>
    
    <p>To the ideologues currently embroiled in the current con&#64258;ict, a spiritual conception of reconciliation suggests this: if you must change your position in order to resolve the crisis that is tearing your country apart, regard these changes not as compromises, but as self-sacrificial acts that are part of the price of reconciliation. </p>
    
    <p>And to the religious groups, especially Christian groups, heavily engaged as combatants in America&rsquo;s ideological civil war: if the most central doctrine of your faith is not your position on abortion or same-sex marriage, but the reconciliation of human beings to God and to each other, should you not then be serving first and foremost as self-sacrificial mediators of the conflict? </p>
    
    <p>Lincoln didn&rsquo;t just talk the talk of self-sacri&#64257;ce in the cause of reconciliation. One month after the delivery of his second inaugural address, and only a few days after the end of the Civil War, his own life was sacrificed for the cause to which he had selflessly dedicated himself.  </p>
    
    <p><em>Preston Manning is the president and CEO of the Manning Centre for Building Democracy</em></p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Business</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Boardroom blunders</hedline>
    
    <abstract>SNC-Lavalin has one of the most distinguished boards in Canada, yet under its watch, executives allegedly engaged in fraud and corruption. What went wrong? </abstract>
    
    <byline>Tamsin McMahon and Chris Sorensen</byline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_LAVALIN01.jpg"></photo>
 
    <photo.caption>Exposed: Former CEO Pierre Duhaime was charged last month with fraud and forgery</photo.caption>
 
    
  <photo.byline>Graham Hughes/Canadian Press</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Less than a week before its former CEO, Pierre Duhaime, was arrested by Quebec police investigators, SNC-Lavalin announced it had received an award for excellence in corporate governance from the Canadian Institute of Chartered Accountants&mdash;the seventh time it won the award in the past decade. </p>
    
    <p>As one of the world&rsquo;s largest engineering firms, with 32,000 employees and projects ranging from airports to water-treatment plants in more than 100 countries, SNC-Lavalin has cultivated a board of directors that could serve as a who&rsquo;s who of Canadian business. It includes: EnCana Corp. founding CEO Gwyn Morgan, former York University president Lorna Marsden, Canadian National Railway Co. CEO Claude Mongeau, and, until recently, Conservative Senator Hugh Segal. Among them are three recipients of the Order of Canada. Many of the directors have served on SNC-Lavalin&rsquo;s board for years. </p>
    
    <p>Yet despite the board&rsquo;s impeccable credentials, on its watch, senior executives at the firm are now alleged to have misappropriated millions to influence the awarding of big contracts both at home and abroad, and then covered their tracks by earmarking the payments for unrelated projects. The Quebec police have charged Duhaime&mdash;who resigned in March&mdash;with fraud, reportedly in connection with a contract to build and design a new $1.3-billion &ldquo;super hospital&rdquo; in Montreal. Authorities are also looking to charge Riadh Ben Aissa, who led SNC-Lavalin&rsquo;s construction business from the company&rsquo;s office in Tunisia. Ben Aissa has been indicted in Switzerland as part of an investigation into a money- laundering scheme, which reportedly involved $139 million worth of payments by SNC-Lavalin. Both he and a company vice-president and financial controller, St&eacute;phane Roy, were fired by SNC-Lavalin earlier this year. </p>
    
    <p>So far, SNC-Lavalin has suggested it is the victim of a couple of rogue employees who were promptly dismissed once their transgressions were discovered. Morgan, who has chaired SNC-Lavalin since 2007, said earlier this year that the company is working &ldquo;to put this behind us.&rdquo; A new CEO&mdash;Robert Card, a company outsider&mdash;was hired in August. This week, a spokesperson said there have been &ldquo;substantial advances&rdquo; to address deficiencies identified by the board. </p>
    
    <p>Yet, despite the reassuring message from SNC-Lavalin, there remain more troubling questions than answers as the scandal continues to unfold. Why was Duhaime permitted to &ldquo;step down&rdquo; with a generous settlement, given the mounting questions about the depth of his involvement? What about the role of chief financial officer, Gilles Laram&eacute;e, who had a problem with the suspicious payments, but apparently took no further action after being overruled by Duhaime? And, given the board&rsquo;s own admission to &ldquo;material weaknesses&rdquo; in some of its corporate policies, why weren&rsquo;t measures taken to guard against questionable behaviour in the first place? (A spokesperson for SNC-Lavalin told <em>Maclean&rsquo;s</em> that no one from the board was available to comment.) </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;[SNC-Lavalin] have done work in emerging markets for a long time, and these types of practices&mdash;bribes or illegal payments to agents&mdash;are, in many cases, how business gets done in these places,&rdquo; says Richard Powers, a business ethics professor at the University of Toronto&rsquo;s Rotman School of Management. &ldquo;So [the board] either knew, or ought to have known, that this was a risk that they faced.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>But the most damning indictment of the board so far has come from SNC-Lavalin&rsquo;s biggest shareholder, investing mogul Stephen Jarislowsky. &ldquo;We have a board that didn&rsquo;t keep its eye on things,&rdquo; Jarislowsky, whose &#64257;rm holds about 14 per cent of the company&rsquo;s stock, told Bloomberg News in April. &ldquo;And the executive more or less operated on its own.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>The public airing of SNC-Lavalin&rsquo;s dirty laundry took a dramatic turn when Duhaime was arrested at his home in Dorval, a suburb of Montreal, on Nov. 28. Until that moment, much of the attention had been focused on Ben Aissa&rsquo;s activities in North Africa&mdash;namely, a bizarre plot cooked up by a couple of outside contractors, once hired by SNC-Lavalin, to smuggle one of the late Moammar Gadhafi&rsquo;s sons out of Libya after the regime fell last year. Suddenly, the scandal returned to Canada&mdash;landing smack in the middle of SNC-Lavalin&rsquo;s own backyard. </p>
    
    <p>The province&rsquo;s anti-corruption unit charged Duhaime, 58, with fraud, conspiring to commit fraud and forgery. Although investigators revealed few other details, the charges came on the heels of a police raid of the McGill University Health Centre, or MUHC, which has said the investigators were looking into how the hospital contract was awarded. When SNC-Lavalin announced it had won the contract back in July of 2010, Ben Aissa was quoted as saying that &ldquo;for SNC-Lavalin and its partners, this is the materialization of a major project that carries both hope and pride for the MUHC, for Montreal and for Quebec.&rdquo; Now it&rsquo;s become yet another source of embarrassment for a city in the midst of the Charbonneau Commission&rsquo;s high-profile corruption inquiry. To add to the company&rsquo;s grief, Montreal&rsquo;s <em>La Presse</em> newspaper reported that SNC-Lavalin paid $22.5 million to obtain the hospital contract, although the claims have not been proven.  </p>
    
    <p>What is known, according to a &ldquo;voluntary independent review&rdquo; conducted by SNC-Lavalin, is that payments totalling US$22.5 million were made by the company in 2010 and 2011 under what it called &ldquo;a presumed agency agreement.&rdquo; Morgan explained to analysts and investors in March that SNC-Lavalin frequently makes use of agents or consultants when bidding on big construction projects around the world, although he added the typical payment was around $700,000, far below the multi-million-dollar payments that have come under scrutiny in Montreal. He said agents&mdash;often locals&mdash;are widely used throughout the industry to help secure necessary permits, arrange to import necessary materials and labour, and can play a role in settling potential contract disputes. &ldquo;SNC-Lavalin and agency agreements do stipulate that the agent adheres to all applicable laws,&rdquo; Morgan said. &ldquo;Of course . . . these very special unusual circumstances that we&rsquo;ve been investigating, we&rsquo;re trying to determine whether that was or wasn&rsquo;t the case.&rdquo; The same internal review, released in March, found that $33.5 million was paid to another agent in connection with a separate unnamed project in 2011. In both cases, the agreements were allegedly requested by Ben Aissa and were earmarked for &ldquo;construction projects to which they did not relate,&rdquo; according to the company. </p>
    
    <p>Morgan declined to name the projects or agents in question or where they were located, citing company policies. Equally unclear was why Duhaime was permitted to resign and collect a severance package worth nearly $5 million after he &ldquo;authorized or permitted&rdquo; the suspect payments. When asked why Duhaime wasn&rsquo;t fired for failing to follow company policy, Morgan said there was no reason to believe Duhaime intended to do anything wrong. He was faced with a signed contract, Morgan said, &ldquo;and for various reasons, he felt he was obligated to pay the bill. In hindsight, we all regret that.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>The role of Laram&eacute;e, SNC-Lavalin&rsquo;s chief financial officer and a company veteran of 25 years, has also come under scrutiny. The company&rsquo;s internal report revealed that he refused to approve the suspect payments, but was overridden by Duhaime. Did Laram&eacute;e not have a responsibility to report to the audit committee what he believed to be a violation of company rules? Not according to SNC-Lavalin. Ian Bourne, the board&rsquo;s vice chairman, has said Laram&eacute;e &ldquo;did his job&rdquo; by passing his concerns along to Duhaime. &ldquo;We have complete, absolute confidence in our CFO.&rdquo;  </p>
    
    <p>Those who have been following the saga closely question SNC-Lavalin&rsquo;s handling of the affair. &ldquo;At the time of the voluntary independent review, the whole thing was described as being isolated,&rdquo; says Anthony Scilipoti, the executive vice-president of Toronto&rsquo;s Veritas Investment Research. &ldquo;But with each passing day, we&rsquo;re learning how expansive the issues really are.&rdquo;  </p>
    
    <p>Despite what SNC-Lavalin described as an exhaustive internal investigation, including hiring outside auditors with expertise in tracing money, the company admitted earlier that it still had no idea what the payments had been used for, nor who had received them. Senior managers had gone to great pains to cover their tracks, including using private email addresses and &ldquo;protected devices to which the company does not have access.&rdquo; The money, it added, was easy to miss: $56 million in a company that had $1.2 billion in cash and coming from within one of its largest divisions, which wasn&rsquo;t required to break out individual projects in its financial accounting to the board. </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;Clearly, our board of directors can&rsquo;t govern something that they don&rsquo;t know about, or prevent something they are not aware of,&rdquo; Bourne told reporters earlier this year. &ldquo;But what we can do is to examine all of our procedures so that the board can be confident that these kinds of events will not happen again.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>But there was evidence the board had ignored earlier warnings. As early as last December, the company&rsquo;s directors received an anonymous letter with a series of damning allegations, including that money was being funnelled to the Gadhafi family in Libya. While Morgan said the board &ldquo;took note&rdquo; of the allegations, he also made it clear it hadn&rsquo;t taken them too seriously. &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve run pretty major companies, and I&rsquo;ve received anonymous letters before that have no credibility,&rdquo; he said in May. </p>
    
    <p>Board members also admitted there were significant &ldquo;material weaknesses&rdquo; in some of the company procedures they oversaw, including the fact that a subsidiary called SNC-Lavalin International Inc. had sole control over contracts with overseas &ldquo;commercial agents,&rdquo; and that its code of ethics didn&rsquo;t actually require employees and executives to report their suspicions of wrongdoing.  </p>
    
    <p>Since learning of the problems in February, the board says it worked quickly to overhaul its processes. Among the changes, authority for hiring overseas &ldquo;agents&rdquo; will now fall to an Agent Review Committee. Agents hired on contract will have to take formal training on the company&rsquo;s code of ethics. Even as the board defended Laram&eacute;e&rsquo;s curious decision not to report concerns he had with the illicit payments, the company now says its CFO will report directly to the chair of the audit committee. </p>
    
    <p>Standing in front of a packed audience at the Toronto Board of Trade for the annual general meeting in May, Morgan said the company was turning a new leaf. &ldquo;It is hard to imagine any board could have taken more decisive action,&rdquo; he told investors.  </p>
    
    <p>Powers agrees it can be difficult for a board, which meets fewer than a dozen times a year outside of committees, to stop a determined employee from committing a fraudulent act. &ldquo;Now, hopefully, you&rsquo;ll have some processes in place to ferret out the fraud, but it&rsquo;s very difficult to stop it immediately,&rdquo; he says, estimating that about 85 per cent of the information a board gets about a company&rsquo;s operators comes directly from management. Similarly, Karl Moore, a business professor at McGill University, says Canadian boards have gradually been moving away from their reputation as part-time figureheads and taking more active role in the companies they oversee. But there remains a precarious relationship between directors and their executives, with board members reluctant to dig too deeply into the day-to-day operations of a company. &ldquo;After something like this happens, the board is going to pay more attention to it,&rdquo; Moore says. &ldquo;But if you start meddling too much, you&rsquo;re going to frustrate your senior team by putting your long nose in their business.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>However, critics say the SNC-Lavalin board simply wasn&rsquo;t doing its job. &ldquo;There&rsquo;s no justification for a board ducking behind the old excuse, &lsquo;I was deceived by management,&rsquo; &rdquo; said Don Thain, a professor emeritus at the Richard Ivey School of Business at the University of Western Ontario and an expert in corporate governance. &ldquo;The board can duck and spin and misrepresent its way out of this, but they are ultimately responsible for the mess, and they should have known better.&rdquo; The role of a board of directors is to know the ins and outs of company business, police the corporate culture and regularly haul executives into the boardroom for a grilling, he says. The problem is that, too often, executives see their board memberships as prestige appointments that don&rsquo;t require the same scrutiny as their own companies. &ldquo;Being well-respected and experienced is no excuse for not doing your job,&rdquo; Thain says. &ldquo;Forget about the committees and all the superficial process stuff that goes on. The central issue that every director should be required to answer is: What would I do if this were my company?&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>SNC-Lavalin&rsquo;s scandal is far from over. Ben Aissa is still being investigated overseas and the RCMP is reportedly working with Swiss police. It&rsquo;s likely more charges will be laid, possibly raising further questions about SNC-Lavalin&rsquo;s senior executives. It all points to a troubling truth about the anemic state of corporate governance in Canada. &ldquo;You can have great written procedures,&rdquo; says Scilipoti. &ldquo;But if they&rsquo;re not respected or enforced, then they&rsquo;re not worth the paper they&rsquo;re printed on.&rdquo; </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Hyped up on snack food</hedline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_BIZNOTEMERGE.jpg"></photo>
 
    <photo.caption>Sugar rush: Cracker Jack is one of several food brands now adding caffeine to its recipes </photo.caption>
 
  <photo.byline>Photo Illustration By Lauren Cattermole;  Courtesy Mcor Technologies</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Cracker Jack is jacking up its popcorn with a new caffeine-infused version of the confection. Parent company Frito-Lay says the candy, called Cracker Jack&rsquo;D, will be marketed in the U.S. only to adults, but the Center for Science in the Public Interest is raising alarm over the product, which will contain approximately 70 mg of caffeine in a two-ounce package (roughly the amount found in half a cup of coffee). In a letter to the U.S. Food and Drug Administration, the health advocacy group says Cracker Jack&rsquo;D is part of an alarming trend of adding caffeine to foods that are traditionally caffeine-free. Other caffeinated products released recently include a &ldquo;water enhancer&rdquo; from Kraft, jellybeans, waffles, syrup and even potato chips, as food manufacturers look to mimic the wild success of the energy drink sector, worth an estimated $8.9 billion in U.S. sales in 2011.</p>
    
     <byline>Emily Senger</byline>
 
    
  <p>One-stop factory</p>
  
    <p>Shoppers at Staples in Europe will soon be picking up a different kind of printed product. The of&#64257;ce supply giant plans to bring 3D printers to selected stores in Belgium and the Netherlands. Starting next year, customers can upload files online and collect in-store their finished three-dimensional objects&mdash;from architectural and medical models to product prototypes. The move may be the first step in making 3D printing widely available to the masses. Three-dimensional printing, which allows people to produce small objects (typically made of plastic or paper material) from computer code, has been hailed by many as the next great technological leap, but prohibitive costs have stalled its widespread adoption so far. The printers range in price from $3,000 to $20,000. Staples, which has partnered with a 3D printer maker called Mcor Technologies, says it plans to quickly expand its &ldquo;Easy 3D&rdquo; program to other countries.</p>
    
     <byline>Mika Rekai</byline>
 
    
  <p>A Bet on Blackberry</p>
    
 
    <p>With its much-anticipated new smartphones still weeks from release, Research In Motion found itself under attack yet again last week. Rival Nokia filed a lawsuit against the BlackBerry maker after a Swedish arbitration panel ruled RIM was in breach of a key wireless patent. At the same time, Yahoo CEO Marissa Mayer was widely quoted dissing RIM&rsquo;s phones: &ldquo;We literally are moving the company from BlackBerrys to smartphones,&rdquo; said Mayer in an interview with <em>Fortune</em>. </p>
    
    <p>Yet despite the bad press, things are suddenly looking up for the Waterloo, Ont.-based firm. Goldman Sachs recently raised its rating on RIM from &ldquo;neutral&rdquo; to &ldquo;buy.&rdquo; Market confidence has been quietly rising. National Bank and Jefferies have also boosted their outlooks. Over the past two months, RIM shares have risen 75 per cent, to over $11. </p>
    
    <p>Investors don&rsquo;t expect RIM to shoot back to the top of the mobile industry when BlackBerry 10 arrives. But it has fallen so far in recent years that even a modest turnaround seems a safe bet that could yield results. &ldquo;We now assess a 30 per cent chance of success for BB10 given positive early reviews, broad-based carrier support, attractive features and interest by carriers and consumers in broadening the field beyond Android/iOS,&rdquo; said Goldman Sachs in its report.</p>
    
    <byline>Toban Dyck</byline>
 
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Royal Baby</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Grace under pressure</hedline>
    
    <abstract>In the 18 months since their wedding, Kate and William have toured Canada and served as cheerleaders-in-chief at the Summer Olympics. Together they will face a hyper-scrutinized pregnancy.</abstract>
    
    
  <byline>Ken MacQueen</byline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_ROYALS_MACQUEEN01.jpg"></photo>
  <photo.caption>Brilliant timing: The birth of an heir would cap a &lsquo;terrific year&rsquo; for the royal family</photo.caption>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>The statement Monday from St. James&rsquo;s Palace had all the hallmarks of a rush job: &ldquo;Their royal highnesses the duke and duchess of Cambridge are very pleased to announce that the duchess of Cambridge is expecting a baby,&rdquo; began the terse statement. After a nod to the happy relatives, it concluded with the meat of the matter: &ldquo;The duchess was admitted this afternoon to King Edward VII Hospital in central London with<em> Hyperemesis gravidarum</em>. As the pregnancy is in its very early stages, her royal highness is expected to stay in hospital for several days and will require a period of rest thereafter.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p> As any parent will tell you, children have minds of their own, and so it was the potential future king or queen of Britain, Canada and 14 other realms who set the agenda in a most unpleasant way.  <em>Hyperemesis gravidarum (HG), </em>as most everyone now knows, is a severe form of nausea and vomiting, an amped-up morning sickness that must have made Kate&rsquo;s weekend visit to her parents&rsquo; home in Bucklebury, Berkshire, a hellish experience. Protocol should have dictated that William&rsquo;s granny, Queen Elizabeth II, would have been the first to know her third great-grandchild and heir was on the way. But even if the couple hadn&rsquo;t chosen that weekend to share the news of the pregnancy, Kate&rsquo;s parents, Carole and Michael Middleton, would have surmised it soon enough as their usually unflappable 30-year-old daughter made repeated dashes for the nearest bathroom. By Monday, her nausea was severe enough that a worried William was on the phone to doctors. That afternoon, he drove her into the city to King Edward VII, &ldquo;London&rsquo;s foremost private hospital.&rdquo; He stayed with her until about 8:20 p.m. Monday, returning to the hospital Tuesday morning. </p>
    
    <p>With police guards at the door and in the street and William pacing the floor, news of Kate&rsquo;s hospitalization was certain to leak out, and with that an unholy mix of rumour and speculation. While most modern couples prefer to keep things secret until the second trimester, the couple had little choice but to release the news while the pregnancy was, as the palace noted, in its &ldquo;very early stages.&rdquo; Speculation puts the pregnancy at less than 12 weeks, meaning conception took place after their carefree, clothes-free visit to Provence and the ch&acirc;teau owned by William&rsquo;s cousin, Viscount Linley.  </p>
    
    <p>The <em>Daily Mail</em>, citing sources, said the couple hadn&rsquo;t planned on sharing the good news until the royal family was gathered for Christmas at Sandringham. Instead, Queen Elizabeth II and William&rsquo;s father, Prince Charles, learned of the pregnancy Monday along with the rest of the royals, barely an hour before a public announcement was released at 4 p.m. London time. William&rsquo;s brother, Harry, an Apache attack helicopter pilot serving in Afghanistan, received the news via email, the BBC said. A child of any gender from William and Kate (once modernized succession laws are expedited) will bump Harry down a notch from his current rank of third in the line of succession, after his father and William. British Prime Minister David Cameron was in a meeting when an aide slipped him a note with the news in advance of the public announcement. &ldquo;I found it quite difficult to keep it to myself,&rdquo; he said later. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s absolutely wonderful news, and I&rsquo;m delighted for them. I&rsquo;m sure they&rsquo;ll make absolutely brilliant parents.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>The announcement was released by St. James&rsquo;s Palace and tweeted by Clarence House, causing the couple&rsquo;s website there to crash under the immense traffic load. Certainly this is the first royal pregnancy announcement delivered on Twitter, which is symbolic of the careful balance William and Kate will have to strike between hidebound royal tradition and modern-day reality. The Twitter hashtag <em>#royalbaby</em> went instantly viral, and within an hour an inevitable spoof account, <em>@RoyalFoetus</em> (&ldquo;Live-tweeting from inside the royal womb&rdquo;), was born. Sample tweets: &ldquo;Hello world. All shall kneel before me,&rdquo; and &ldquo;My spoon is currently umbilical. Silver awaits on exit.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Concern over the state of Kate&rsquo;s health has sucked some joy out of the announcement, though there is little doubt that Kate, said to be on an intravenous drip, is receiving care several notches above National Health Service standards. After all, the royal patron of King Edward VII is the Queen herself. The BBC says Kate is being cared for by a team including gynecologist Marcus Setchell, who delivered the two children of Sophie, countess of Wessex and wife of the Queen&rsquo;s youngest son, Prince Edward. Hyperemesis gravidarum, which translates loosely, and rather bluntly, from the Latin as &ldquo;excessive vomiting of pregnant women,&rdquo; strikes less than one per cent of women in the first trimester, according to some experts. If treated promptly, it usually poses no harm to the baby, though it can leave the mother exhausted, dehydrated, unable to face food and profoundly miserable. The usual treatment involves intravenous replacement of fluids and nutrients and anti-nausea medication to prevent major weight loss. </p>
    
    <p>William spent six hours at the hospital with his wife Tuesday as she prepared for a third day hooked up to an intravenous drip. The couple issued a statement released by St. James&rsquo;s Palace: &ldquo;Kate and the duke are immensely grateful for the good wishes they have received.&rdquo; A spokesman said Kate is &ldquo;continuing to feel better&rdquo; although she remains exhausted. There were no indications when she might be released. </p>
    
    <p>It wasn&rsquo;t long before women were trotting out horror stories about their experiences with HG. &ldquo;Any movement, any sound, any smell just makes you vomit,&rdquo; Caitlin Dean told the <em>Daily Mail</em> in a Technicolour recitation of her experience. &ldquo;I vomited 20 to 30 times a day for the first few months. In the latter part it was just once or twice a day, but it&rsquo;s still unpleasant.&rdquo; Caroline Jones, a 35-year-old north London mother, told the <em>Daily Mirror</em> about her hospitalization and near five-month battle with HG before the healthy birth of her daughter Mia two years ago. &ldquo;Forget morning sickness, this was any time of day sickness,&rdquo; she said. &ldquo;During the day I could eat nothing, as the mere thought of food made me gag.&rdquo; Acupuncture offered her the best temporary relief, she said.  </p>
    
    <p>Maria Shriver, estranged wife of Arnold Schwarzenegger and a mother of four, tweeted in solidarity with the duchess. &ldquo;Wonderful news for Prince William and Kate. Kate has Hyperemesis. Had that with my last child. Not fun at all. Hang in there Kate.&rdquo;  </p>
    
    <p>William&rsquo;s mother, Diana&mdash;who was pregnant just four months after marrying Charles in 1981&mdash;suffered from months of morning sickness. That, and self-consciousness, curtailed her public appearances. &ldquo;The whole world is watching my stomach,&rdquo; Diana complained. A similar fate awaits Kate as she shoves her form-fitting clothes to the back of the closet and braces for a long, and no doubt stylish, gestation, lived out far longer in the public eye than she would have wished. </p>
    
    <p>Remarkably, the duchess was in fine public form only last Friday. She combined her trip to see her parents with a visit to St. Andrew&rsquo;s, her former prep school in Berkshire. There, she lunched on Scottish beef and &ldquo;bird seed,&rdquo; a dessert that combines pancakes and Rice Krispies. After lunch, she took some practice shots on the field hockey grounds. She also gave a formal speech to the gathered students, part of her increasing independent responsibilities as a royal. School officials admitted Monday they had no clue the duchess was pregnant. In retrospect, after that school lunch the day could have ended disastrously. No surprise, then, that the palace has prescribed &ldquo;a period of rest&rdquo; for Kate once she leaves the hospital. The prospect of a public loss of lunch is one ruinous photo opportunity senior royals will avoid at all costs. </p>
    
    <p>The British press, after speculating about a royal pregnancy virtually from April 29, 2011, the day the couple married, found itself scooped by a press release, no doubt hampered by their recent inability to hack royal cellphones. Reporters and editors reacted with the level of restraint for which they are noted&mdash;which is to say little or none at all. Royal correspondents instantly assumed the role of all-knowing meddlesome mothers-in-law. Ah-ha! This is why she toasted with water during the couple&rsquo;s recent Diamond Jubilee visit to Singapore. Why William accepted with a smile when a woman handed him a handmade baby onesie decorated with a helicopter and the phrase: &ldquo;Daddy&rsquo;s little co-pilot.&rdquo; And why Kate suddenly changed her hairstyle to feathered layers and long bangs&mdash;clearly a diversionary tactic to draw attention from below the waist. Fiendishly clever! Piers Morgan, the former British tabloid editor turned CNN television host, fired a tweet across the bow of his former colleagues: &ldquo;Congratulations to every magazine editor for calling Kate&rsquo;s pregnancy&mdash;especially those who did covers on it 11 months ago.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>The <em>Daily Mail</em>  advised her on the healthy stuff she should be eating, assuming she can keep it down, and what to avoid: &ldquo;P&acirc;t&eacute;, liver, shark, marlin, raw shellfish, mould-ripened soft cheese, partially cooked eggs and meat.&rdquo; As if. Mercifully, Scottish beef and bird seed aren&rsquo;t on the forbidden list.  </p>
    
    <p>The prospect of an heir&mdash;or heirs, as some punters would have it&mdash;being delivered in the summer of 2013 is brilliant timing, extending a royal run of good news that began with William and Kate&rsquo;s engagement in November 2010 and continued with their wedding in 2011, then this year&rsquo;s successful Olympic Games and the Diamond Jubilee marking the Queen&rsquo;s 60-year reign. Children were always in the plan&mdash;the overarching duty of a royal wife being production of an heir. But as William made clear in their first post-engagement interview, it would happen on their timetable. &ldquo;We&rsquo;ll get over the marriage thing first and then we&rsquo;ll look at the kids. But obviously we want a family so we&rsquo;ll have to start thinking about that.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Unlike Diana&mdash;engaged at 19, virgin bride at 20 and mother to William before her 21st birthday&mdash;the couple bided their time, giving Kate a chance to settle into an increasing level of royal duties, though in some respects her apprenticeship started not long after the two first set eyes on each other in 2001 as students at the University of St. Andrews in Scotland.  </p>
    
    <p>They may well have decided to delay parenthood to allow William to focus on his career as an RAF search and rescue helicopter pilot in Wales, and to leave themselves free for some post-marriage familiarization tours: their wildly successful cross-Canada summer tour in 2011, their ubiquitous presence as cheerleaders-in-chief at the 2012 London Summer Olympic Games, and a host of domestic and foreign Diamond Jubilee travels.  </p>
    
    <p>Kate is increasingly comfortable in the presence of the Queen. The two were often seen chatting amiably at Diamond Jubilee events. It&rsquo;s doubtful that Kate being caught out by a paparazzo who peddled topless (and some bottomless) photos of her private vacation time with William in September harmed the relationship. No scandal was involved and the palace&rsquo;s full-on legal attack against the French magazine in question signalled the Queen&rsquo;s and William&rsquo;s desire to protect Kate&rsquo;s privacy and the monarchy&rsquo;s brand. </p>
    
    <p>Ingrid Seward, editor-in-chief of <em>Majesty</em> magazine, said the pregnancy marks a &ldquo;new beginning&rdquo; for the Firm. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s very important for the monarchy. This is the way forward. This is the first child who will be an heir to the throne whatever sex they are,&rdquo; she told an interviewer. Pregnancies frequently turn women, royal or not, into semi-public property, and, like others in the British press, Seward isn&rsquo;t above speculating on the couple&rsquo;s most intimate intentions. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s the culmination of a terrific year,&rdquo; she said, &ldquo;and what Kate really wanted&mdash;to get pregnant in a Jubilee year.&rdquo; Well, perhaps. </p>
    
    <p>How the couple will raise wee Charles or Philip and/or Victoria, Elizabeth, Diana or whatever the little co-pilot is called, is also a topic of discussion. It&rsquo;s likely the couple&rsquo;s bare-bones staff will be expanded to include a nanny. The demands of royal life, quite apart from tradition, would almost dictate as much.  </p>
    
    <p>For William and Harry, who grew up in the tumult of their parents&rsquo; fractious, deteriorating relationship, nannies were a source of stability and love, as well as loss. Barbara Barnes was the children&rsquo;s beloved nanny during their earliest years. William would frequently climb into bed with her as a toddler before they&rsquo;d get up for breakfast. But Diana, increasingly insecure and threatened by William&rsquo;s bond with his &ldquo;Baba,&rdquo; dismissed her on a flimsy pretext when he was just 4, said Penny Junor, a veteran royal watcher and author of <em>Prince William: Born to be King, which was</em> published earlier this year. Afterwards William became less outgoing and trusting, Junor said in an interview with <em>Maclean&rsquo;s</em>. &ldquo;The only explanation is that she was so tied up with her own feelings that she couldn&rsquo;t look beyond them to see what this would do to her sons.&rdquo; Notably, Barnes was one of the first names William added to his wedding-guest list, 24 years after her departure. </p>
    
    <p>Later, Diana tried to undermine Tiggy Legge-Bourke, a fun-loving aristocrat who served as a minder and companion for the boys under Charles&rsquo;s watch as they approached adolescence. Junor said Diana started unfounded rumours that Charles was sleeping with Legge-Bourke but failed to have her removed. Diana&rsquo;s own childhood was difficult, scarred by frequent violent arguments between her parents. Her mother lost custody of the children after she fled the marriage for another man when Diana was 6. </p>
    
    <p>While Diana&rsquo;s childhood was played out behind estate walls, William and Harry, to their horror, saw their parents&rsquo; arguments, infidelities and custody issues laid bare in the press and in television documentaries as they waged an all-too-public campaign for hearts and minds. &ldquo;People are so aware of what happened to Charles and Diana and what a difficult time William had that they are incredibly protective of him,&rdquo; Junor said.  </p>
    
    <p>For all the strife, there is no doubt that both parents loved their sons deeply. Diana, for all her emotional instability, gave her sons a gift that Charles certainly never had: the chance to mingle with other children in daycares and junior schools, to visit fairs and water parks and to learn from people with mental, physical or financial challenges who were at the core of Diana&rsquo;s charitable endeavours. </p>
    
    <p>Diana&rsquo;s death in a Paris car crash in August 1997 was, of course, the ultimate abandonment. It marked William, then 15, and Harry, 12, in ways we cannot possibly know. &ldquo;They weren&rsquo;t allowed to keep the grief to themselves,&rdquo; said Junor, &ldquo;they had to share it with the whole world.&rdquo; That years later the boys&rsquo; phones would be hacked by the media, and that revealing long-lens photos of William&rsquo;s intimate holiday with Kate in France this year would be splashed across magazines and the Internet, only confirms the price he pays as a public royal.  </p>
    
    <p>How will William raise his family? With as much privacy as humanly possible, something both he and Kate must ponder with alarm as hundreds of members of the media and public mass outside King Edward VII Hospital. Expect protocols that limit media access to any young heirs at events like christenings and birthdays. Such restrictions worked reasonably well when William and Harry were young, at least until their parents&rsquo; own media campaigns thrust them into the spotlight. </p>
    
    <p>It&rsquo;s little wonder that William has grown close to the Middleton family, who by all outward appearances gave their three children the kind of serene upper-middle-class upbringing that he could only dream of. Together in semi-rural Bucklebury, they have had fun nights at the local pub and home-cooked dinners full of wine and laughter. No butlers, no protocol, no staged leaks to the press. It&rsquo;s entirely fitting that circumstances resulted in the Middletons being the first to learn of Kate&rsquo;s pregnancy, no matter how wretchedly the news was announced. &ldquo;I hope we&rsquo;ll be able to have a happy family ourselves,&rdquo; she said in an interview as she spoke of her family. &ldquo;They&rsquo;ve been great over the years, helping me with difficult times. We see a lot of each other, and they&rsquo;re very close to me.&rdquo; Kate&rsquo;s parents are &ldquo;over the moon&rdquo; at the prospect of a grandchild, reports John Haley, landlord of the Old Boot Inn, the local pub in Stanford Dingley.  </p>
    
    <p>Kate will be a 31-year-old mother if the pregnancy goes smoothly, old for the production of a royal heir but hardly out of step with the times. With that also comes a level of maturity, comfort and fun, as Canadians saw during their tour here: playful asides, gentle caresses, comfortable silences.   </p>
    
    <p>The couple had the luxury of time to grow together this past decade, something Charles and Diana certainly lacked before William&rsquo;s arrival. William already has his co-pilot, his recent gift of a baby onesie notwithstanding. They&rsquo;ve faced much together already; there can be few surprises between them.  </p>
    
    <p>They will also face a difficult, hyper-scrutinized pregnancy, regardless of how long the morning sickness lasts. And after that, if all goes well, the challenges of any parents, coupled with the expectations of a country and a Commonwealth. &ldquo;Our promise to Canada is that we shall return,&rdquo; William said as their Canadian tour neared a close in Calgary. And if it&rsquo;s with baby in tow, so much the better. </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Royal Baby</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Game of thrones</hedline>
    
    <abstract>The pregnancy is fraught with a constitutional  hitch that should be  sorted out by 2015</abstract>
    
    <byline>John Fraser</byline>
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_ROYALS_SUCCESSION01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>Coronation chair: Since 1308, all but two monarchs have been crowned in this chair</photo.caption>
    
  <photo.byline>HUSSEIN ANWAR/SIPA</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>If Kate ever wondered after her storybook wedding what it would be like when the full force of royal expectations and demands descended upon her, she knows it now. The ordinary miracle of pregnancy shared by a happy couple anywhere is always a cause for celebration, but a first pregnancy in the direct line of succession to the Crown was always bound to bring on a media frenzy. This one also comes complete with a historic constitutional blizzard. </p>
    
    <p>The news that she and Prince William, the duchess and duke of Cambridge, are expecting their first child in a little over seven months will be greeted with joy in many quarters, indifference in some and gnashing of teeth in still others. That&rsquo;s normal in an egalitarian age when deference to royalty vanished a long time ago but residual and even renewed and growing affection for Queen Elizabeth II and her &ldquo;heirs and successors&rdquo; has surprised many observers. </p>
    
    <p>But this particular pregnancy is also fraught with constitutional heavy traffic, the likes of which royal watchers have not seen in a long time. For starters, the current law of succession in all of Elizabeth II&rsquo;s realms&mdash;and there are 16 of them, including the United Kingdom and Canada&mdash;says a first-born girl can be trumped by a younger brother. </p>
    
    <p>In a historic agreement at the Commonwealth heads of government meeting in Australia last year&mdash;Oct. 28, 2011, to be exact&mdash;all the countries which have Queen Elizabeth II as head of state agreed to change this and one other antique law rooted in the denominational wars of past centuries (that the spouse of a monarch cannot be a Roman Catholic). That was greeted everywhere by acclaim, but the problem is that they have not changed it yet, and 16 different legislatures are not likely to get their acts together in time for this baby&rsquo;s arrival sometime next summer. (They&rsquo;ve set themselves a 2015 deadline.) </p>
    
    <p>That&rsquo;s not a problem, according to British Prime Minister David Cameron. The plan is to backdate any future legislation on the laws of succession to that October 2011 agreement in Australia. Regardless of whether it is a girl or a boy, then, she or he will one day be the reigning monarch and at birth will automatically become third in line to the throne, after the Prince of Wales and the child&rsquo;s father, Prince William. </p>
    
    <p>So that would seem to look after all the possible constitutional sticking points, which may or may not be a comfort to poor Kate, who was admitted to the King Edward VII Hospital thanks to acute morning sickness. In ordinary pregnancies, a couple is allowed some privacy to get through this period, which brings joy and anxiety in equal measure. In ordinary pregnancies, it is never wise to announce the happy event until the first trimester has passed, for good reasons. In ordinary pregnancies, the expectant mother would be able to go about her business with quiet, sustaining pride, free of frantic photographers and creepy tabloid doyens who will afflict the poor duchess right up to the moment of delivery with half-baked advice, old wives&rsquo; tales and censorious criticisms about her weight and etc. etc. etc. Just wait for it! </p>
    
    <p>The Kate that people got to know over the past few years is an intensely private woman, so one can safely speculate that the necessity of announcing this pregnancy so soon would have brought her some real distress. The one thing royal officials know, however, is not to lie, so when she had to be admitted to hospital, the pregnancy also had to be acknowledged. Just one reign ago, in the latter years of King George VI, had Princess Elizabeth, as the heiress presumptive in 1948, suffered serious morning sickness when she was pregnant with Prince Charles, she would have been treated at the palace and would never have gone to hospital. In any event, the world would never have known, or at least not so soon. </p>
    
    <p>On the day of the big news, Prime Minister Stephen Harper issued a statement: &ldquo;We recall with great fondness the 2011 royal tour of Canada by the duke and duchess of Cambridge. The tremendous outpouring of affection with which Canadians greeted the royal couple is bolstered by today&rsquo;s happy news. On behalf of all Canadians, Laureen and I convey our warmest congratulations to both the duke and the duchess.&rdquo; All good stuff. </p>
    
    <p>Meanwhile, some pretty arch comments were afflicting the Internet. One of my favourites was a self-appointed royal &ldquo;necromancer&rdquo; named James Kirkup, writing a blog for the <em>Daily Telegraph</em> in London. This required working out a few royal death dates, never a happy subject with monarchists (but a favourite of Canadian republicans who keep being chagrined at the longevity of the Queen). This game all led to the sport of calculating what year William and Kate&rsquo;s &#64257;rst child would ascend the throne. </p>
    
    <p>Looking at average life expectancies of someone like William, born in 1982, King William V has a good chance of lasting quite a few years, 86 to be exact. So, says Kirkup, Kate and William&rsquo;s baby may well become king or queen around 2068, at the age of 56, and rule right into the 22nd century. To which we say, long live the future queen or king. 
    </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Royal Baby</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Bringing up baby in the Royal fishbowl</hedline>
  
  <abstract>Can Will and Kate give their child a semblance of a private life?</abstract>
    
    <byline>Jonathon Gatehouse</byline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_ROYALS_HEIR02.jpg"></photo>
  <photo.caption>His first photo op: Charles and Diana introduce a newborn Prince William to the world outside St. Mary&rsquo;s Hospital</photo.caption>
    
  <photo.byline>John Stillwell/PA PHOTOS/KEYSTONE PRESS</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Prince William&rsquo;s first public engagement came just 22 hours after his birth: a brief appearance on the steps of St. Mary&rsquo;s Hospital in London, swaddled in a blanket and held in the awkward clutch of his father, Charles. As the crowd cheered, reporters bellowed and cameras strobed, the jug-eared heir to the British throne dutifully displayed his own, far more telegenic successor. Then he handed the infant off to a shyly smiling Diana, steered her gently by the various photographers&rsquo; positions and opened the rear door to their chauffeur-driven station wagon as the new family prepared to speed off home. </p>
    
    <p>Thirty years on, the most striking thing about the footage is the absence of a car seat, or even seat belts for that matter. But the carefully choreographed unveiling was groundbreaking for its time. William Arthur Philip Louis was the first future sovereign to be born in a hospital. His father was actually there to witness his arrival. And, as with the couple&rsquo;s fairy-tale wedding 11 months before, the public and press had been invited to share the joy almost every step of the way. The news of his birth may have been declared with a traditional 41-gun salute at the Tower of London, but there were modern touches mixed in as well. William would never be a commoner, but his parents, it seemed, were determined that he might find some common ground with them.  </p>
    
    <p>It&rsquo;s a balancing act that has come to define the young prince&rsquo;s life: small, often stolen bits of normalcy that leaven his singular existence as a future monarch and global celebrity. Early on, they came mostly at the insistence of his mother&mdash;a woman raised in privilege, but not under constant scrutiny. Small escapes like outings to public playgrounds with his brother, Harry, or trips to movies or theme parks dressed in jeans and ball cap rather than the double-breasted suits and ties that function as the uniform for male members of the Windsor clan. Later, they stemmed from his own choices and bargains with the insatiable media, such as a post-high-school &ldquo;gap year&rdquo; spent working in anonymity on a dairy farm, travelling in Africa and volunteering as a teacher in Chile in exchange for a few sit-down interviews and the occasional photo op. And since his marriage to the former Kate Middleton in April 2011, they have presumably become joint decisions, like the one that saw the young couple eschew palace life in London in favour of a cottage on the Isle of Anglesey off the northwest coast of Wales&mdash;close to his job piloting rescue helicopters for the Royal Air Force and remote enough to discourage all but the heartiest paparazzi.  </p>
    
    <p>But now, with the impending birth of their first child next year&mdash;destined to become third in line for the throne, regardless of sex&mdash;the challenge for Will and Kate becomes how to protect, and perhaps even expand, those precious private moments in a world that is ever more plugged in and hungry for gossip. In recent years, even the 86-year-old Queen has come to grips with the need to transform herself from aloof monarch to accessible celebrity, going so far as to &ldquo;sky dive&rdquo; on film with Daniel Craig&rsquo;s James Bond for the opening ceremonies of the London Olympics. Can the public dissemination of the royal ultrasounds be far behind? </p>
    
    <p>The dangers of over-sharing are all too apparent to William. After all, he had barely started school when his parents&rsquo; marriage began to unravel in the press. The early promise of their union&mdash;still a teenager, Diana introduced her husband, the quintessentially stuffy Englishman, to rock music, boxer shorts and blow-dried hair&mdash;was undone by an age difference that was only 12 calendar years, but more like a century in terms of taste, style and outlook. It was the tabloids that finally put an end to the charade in 1992, by first publishing details of intercepted phone calls between Diana and a lover who called her &ldquo;Squidgy,&rdquo; and later, far more lurid conversations between Charles and his longtime mistress Camilla Parker Bowles. An official separation came that December, followed by a &ldquo;War of the Waleses,&rdquo; waged through tell-all books and all too candid interviews. Charles told the BBC that he had never loved his bride, and Diana responded in kind on ITV. &ldquo;There were three of us in this marriage, so it was a bit crowded.&rdquo; Neither seemed above using their boys to score points or court public sympathy, with Diana going so far as to share a story about crying in a locked bathroom after one particularly nasty fight while 10-year-old &ldquo;Wills&rdquo; crouched outside, stuffing tissues under the door. It wasn&rsquo;t until the couple divorced, in the summer of 1996, that things started to settle down. </p>
    
    <p>And it was only after their mother&rsquo;s tragic death in a Paris traffic accident a year later that William and his brother gained a semblance of a private life. Cowed by public anger over the role the pursuing press played the night Diana died, Britain&rsquo;s newspapers and TV networks struck a deal to leave the boys alone until they turned 18. During their years at Eton&mdash;the elite boys&rsquo; school just beyond the gates of their grandmother&rsquo;s Windsor Castle&mdash;William and Harry were able to live, and occasionally misbehave, just like their peers. And Charles, who remains psychologically scarred by his own odd upbringing&mdash;distant parents, years spent away at a spartan Scottish boarding school, then a stint at Cambridge, the university his mother&rsquo;s courtiers selected for him&mdash;did his best to keep them grounded. The boys&rsquo; exceptionally privileged lives&mdash;ski holidays at Klosters, a private London apartment where they could party with mates&mdash;were balanced with royal duties and calls to service.  </p>
    
    <p>Catherine, duchess of Cambridge, formerly known as Kate Middleton, has a far different story, of course. Descended from wool merchants on her father&rsquo;s side and coal miners on her mother&rsquo;s side, she is from an entirely different social stratum&mdash;the first commoner to marry a future British king in 350 years. Her father, Michael, and mother, Carole, met while they were both working for British Airways. And her childhood family home in Berkshire was a four-bedroom semi-detached rather than a sprawling palace. That the 30-year-old ever got together with a prince is in itself a testament to the U.K.&rsquo;s evolving class system. When Carole was too pregnant with Kate to continue working for the airline, she started a side business making loot bags for children&rsquo;s parties, running it out of a shed in the garden. Within a few years, the company, called Party Pieces, grew large enough that Michael quit his job to help manage the operation. Kate, her sister, Pippa, and brother, James, eventually moved from the local comprehensive to Marlborough College, an expensive prep school. And the family graduated to an estate house in the village of Bucklebury. Far from regal, but respectable enough. Today, the family party business is worth an estimated 30 million pounds, about four times its valuation before Kate married the real life Prince Charming she met while studying at the University of St. Andrews in Scotland.  </p>
    
    <p>One wonders, however, just how much influence she will have over the upbringing of her child. Many of the lessons she absorbed from own parents will not be applicable to life in the royal fishbowl. William kept her on a string for seven years, and even broke up with her for a while before finally proposing during a 2010 Kenyan safari. (Their courtship dragged on so long that the papers dubbed her &ldquo;Waitey Katie.&rdquo;) And she&rsquo;s hardly had time to adjust to the public role, let alone to the palace intrigues that proved the undoing of both Diana and Prince Andrew&rsquo;s ex-wife, Sarah Ferguson, two women who had the advantage of having been brought up in Britain&rsquo;s snobbier precincts.  </p>
    
    <p>On the other hand, things are changing quickly for the British monarchy. A generation ago, it was unthinkable that a divorced man might be king, let alone one who married his mistress. In the wired world, even the announcement of a royal pregnancy must be rushed out, for fear that an unknown blogger or Twitter user will steal the Windsors&rsquo; thunder.  </p>
    
    <p>The soon-to-arrive prince or princess&mdash;a future king or queen&mdash;will be an instant celebrity. It will be a few years before he or she has to worry about tumbling to the tabloid standards of the Kardashians, Lady Gaga and Justin Bieber, but that&rsquo;s surely the way things are heading. After all, naked snaps of Mum and Uncle Harry have already hit the Internet. Being a royal is no longer what it used to be. And the best parenting in the world can&rsquo;t change that.   </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Royal Baby</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Raising a monarch</hedline>
    
    <hedline>The family history is full of examples&mdash;some effective, some not&mdash;to help Will and Kate along the way</hedline>
    
    <byline>Michael Friscolanti</byline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_ROYALS_HEIR01.jpg"></photo>
     <photo.caption>Heir in training: Diana was obsessed with William&rsquo;s public image and tried to expose him to the world outside the palace walls </photo.caption>
 
    
  <photo.byline>MAVRIXPHOTO/KEYSTONE PRESS</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Elizabeth Alexandra Mary, as she was known back in 1936, was 10 years old when all of England heard the scandalous news. Her uncle, King Edward VIII, had abandoned the throne&mdash;ditching his royal obligations in favour of Wallis Simpson, the twice-divorced American woman he had been forbidden to marry. &ldquo;I have found it impossible to carry the heavy burden of responsibility and to discharge my duties as I would wish to do without the help and support of the woman I love,&rdquo; he told his subjects in a stunning December radio address from Windsor. </p>
    
    <p>Elizabeth&rsquo;s father&mdash;Edward&rsquo;s stammering and thoroughly insecure little brother Albert&mdash;was suddenly the king. And Elizabeth, his beloved elder daughter, was now the heiress presumptive. </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;Does that mean you&rsquo;ll be queen?&rdquo; her younger sister, Margaret, famously asked.  </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;Yes, someday,&rdquo; Elizabeth answered, as crowds gathered near the family home. </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;Poor you,&rdquo; Margaret said. </p>
    
    <p>Three generations later, as the house of Windsor prepares for the birth of another heir apparent, Margaret&rsquo;s reaction still rings true: &ldquo;Poor you.&rdquo; Although the parents-to-be are no doubt thrilled (&ldquo;very pleased&rdquo; was the official word out of St. James&rsquo;s Palace), the duke and duchess of Cambridge are well aware of what&rsquo;s looming. The paparazzi. The pressure. Not to mention the double duty that no other parent faces: they have to raise a child and train a future monarch at the same time. </p>
    
    <p>In other words, they need to ensure their offspring isn&rsquo;t another King Edward VIII. </p>
    
    <p>Whether it&rsquo;s the 1200s or the Twitter age, much of the royal curriculum remains the same. Be humble and modest. Be courteous and polite (even to the photographers). Accept your God-given role. And don&rsquo;t, under any circumstances, &ldquo;let the side down.&rdquo; As Prince William himself said on his 21st birthday, when asked if he &ldquo;wanted&rdquo; to be the sovereign: &ldquo;It&rsquo;s not a question of wanting to be. It&rsquo;s something I was born into, and it&rsquo;s my duty.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>How the future king and queen will prepare their child for the throne remains to be seen. But one thing is certain: the family history is full of examples&mdash;some effective, some not&mdash;to guide them along the way. </p>
    
    <p>Before Queen Elizabeth II was the Queen, her father thoroughly groomed her for the job. She was tutored on the Constitution, and encouraged to participate in Christmas plays and other public performances that would prepare her for the spotlight. (&ldquo;Where does she get her poise?&rdquo; her dad once asked, amazed by her confidence on stage.) In 1945, Elizabeth even joined the Auxiliary Territorial Service, learning to drive ambulances and getting her hands greasy changing the oil in military trucks.  </p>
    
    <p>It was her mother who taught her the value of co-operating with the press; if a flashbulb failed to go off, she always made sure the family repeated the pose. &ldquo;When it&rsquo;s your duty, you stick out anything,&rdquo; the Queen Mother once said. </p>
    
    <p>By her 21st birthday, Elizabeth was thoroughly schooled in the disciplines of her inheritance, and embraced her role with open arms. &ldquo;I declare before you all that my whole life, whether it be long or short, shall be devoted to your service,&rdquo; she said in a radio address. Sixty years later, she remains a symbol of the duty and commitment that defines the British monarchy. </p>
    
    <p>But the heirs to her throne&mdash;her son Prince Charles and her grandson William&mdash;were not always as keen as she was. </p>
    
    <p>Charles fondly recalls when he was four years old, watching his mother parading around in St. Edward&rsquo;s crown before her coronation. &ldquo;I remember my mama coming up when we were being bathed as children, wearing the crown,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;It was quite funny.&rdquo; But the Prince of Wales has also publicly complained about his upbringing, saying his mom and dad were more focused on protocol than on parenting. Once, after young Charles stuck out his tongue at a crowd of spectators, his father gave him a good spanking. (Cheating on his wife and dragging the family through a nasty public divorce wasn&rsquo;t part of the kingly syllabus, either.) </p>
    
    <p>The apprenticeship of Prince William had its own hiccups. Although Diana was obsessed with her eldest son&rsquo;s public image&mdash;posing him for the cameras and trying desperately to expose him to the world outside the palace walls&mdash;he loathed the attention. In fact, Diana tearfully confided to friends, &ldquo;William is waiting patiently for the monarchy to be abolished,&rdquo; adding that he had asked: &ldquo;Do I really have to be a part of this family?&rdquo; The prince once told his dad that perhaps he would &ldquo;go backpacking in Nepal and never come back.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>William despised the armed bodyguards almost as much as the paparazzi. During one winter vacation, when a guard tackled him in the snow before he tobogganed into traffic, William reportedly yelled: &ldquo;Why won&rsquo;t you let me be a normal person?&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Sadly, it was his mother&rsquo;s tragic death that provided William with his most valuable hands-on lesson. The 15-year-old heir who so hated the attention seemed to accept his inevitable public role, speaking to mourners and walking, with his brother Harry, behind Diana&rsquo;s funeral procession.  </p>
    
    <p>In the years that followed, William&rsquo;s tutelage only intensified, under the very watchful eye of the Queen. They shared regular tea dates, granny and grandson, which provided her with a chance to mould the future king into a link between the traditions she represents&mdash;responsibility, pomp and protocol&mdash;and the uncertain, ever-evolving monarchy of the 21st century. &ldquo;William has had the lectures,&rdquo; one source explained to a British reporter. &ldquo;He has been told: &lsquo;Don&rsquo;t let the side down.&rsquo; &rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>He has not. While his party-prone brother has generated plenty of tabloid fodder (for smoking marijuana, for wearing a Nazi Halloween costume and, most recently, for naked photos snapped at a Las Vegas hotel party), William has behaved as a proper heir should. He graduated from St. Andrews University, trained as an RAF search-and-rescue helicopter pilot and married the love of his life in a ceremony that gripped the globe. </p>
    
    <p>And, perhaps most importantly, he explained to his future bride exactly what she was getting herself into. More than once, William even gave her the opportunity to back out. She didn&rsquo;t. She walked down the aisle at Westminster Abbey with eyes wide open, fully aware that when she did have a baby, the announcement would trigger exactly the type of media frenzy that&rsquo;s now unfolding. (To be fair, though, Kate probably didn&rsquo;t foresee that the Twitter handle @RoyalFoetus would have 11,000 followers.) </p>
    
    <p>Will her baby grow up to be a teenager with a Twitter account? Will Twitter be obsolete by then? Will the monarchy? </p>
    
    <p>It&rsquo;s only the first trimester, probably a bit too soon to start worrying about those kinds of questions. At the very least, the throne training can wait until after the potty training.  </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Royal Baby</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Naming rights</hedline>
    
    <abstract>William and Kate have to pick a baby name that will be  both modern and historic. No pressure then.</abstract>
    
    <byline>Patricia Treble</byline>
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_ROYALS_BABYNAMES01.jpg"></photo>
  <photo.caption>A future king? A forensic artist imagines a male heir&rsquo;s appearance </photo.caption>
    
  <photo.byline>Joe Mullins/Splash News</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>The minute the pregnancy was announced, bookmakers started taking bets on what name William and Kate would choose. Since this baby will eventually carry the title of &ldquo;Queen&rdquo; or &ldquo;King,&rdquo; a few names can be immediately nixed. The traditionalist couple won&rsquo;t pick anything celebrity-like, so no Peaches or Apple or Blue Ivy for the Windsors. And though Diana will likely be honoured as a secondary name if it&rsquo;s a girl&mdash;Charles and William each have four given names&mdash;her public campaign to stop Charles from becoming monarch makes it unlikely she&rsquo;ll get top billing. Though William adores his granny, Elizabeth is probably out for two reasons: there have already been two British Queen Elizabeths in the last century: the current monarch and her mother. Furthermore, the Belgian heirs snagged the name for <em>their</em> future queen. So here are some early guesses.</p>
    
     
 
  <p>Boy</p>
    
 
    <p>Philip </p>
    
    <p>William and Kate adore his 91-year-old grandfather, Prince Philip, who&rsquo;s been the Queen&rsquo;s &ldquo;rock&rdquo; for 65 years  </p>
    
 
    
    <p>Henry </p>
    
    <p>A close school friend of William and Harry, Henry van Straubenzee was killed in a car accident in 2002. The moniker is also the official name of Prince Harry.  </p>
    
 
    
    <p>Michael </p>
    
    <p>Kate&rsquo;s father, Michael Middleton, is the quiet heart of her solidly middle-class clan. William is famously close to his father-in-law. </p>
    
     
    
    <p>James </p>
    
    <p>For a couple educated at a Scottish university, what better name than that of James VI of Scotland, who united his throne with that of England in 1603?  </p>
    
     
    
    <p>John </p>
    
    <p>He might have lost a lot of royal power in 1215, but by signing the Magna Carta, King John was instrumental in creating the foundations for Western democracy  </p>
    
 
 
 
 
   <p>Girl</p>


   <p>Alexandra </p>
    
    <p>The beautiful, deaf wife of King Edward VII, Alexandra of Denmark captivated Britain and became a devoted patron of charities  </p>
    
     
    
    <p>Victoria </p>
    
    <p>The longest-reigning monarch (to date) came to the throne at the tender age of 18 and gave her name to Britain&rsquo;s greatest century </p>
    
     
    
    <p>Anne </p>
    
    <p>The affection between William and Kate and the Queen&rsquo;s daughter, Princess Anne, could be seen during the Olympics. Her children are close to their Wales cousins.  </p>
    
     
    
    <p>Mary </p>
    
    <p>The Queen&rsquo;s grandmother, Queen Mary, was the consort of George V. Notoriously stiff and reserved in public, she was adored by Elizabeth.  </p>
    
     
    
    <p>Charlotte </p>
    
    <p>England loved Princess Charlotte, who was expected to be queen after her father, George IV. Her death, during childbirth, plunged the nation into deep mourning. </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Royal Baby</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Lights, cameras, pregnancy</hedline>
    
    <abstract>Royal mums-to-be once hid in blowsy dresses and coats&mdash;or vanished from view. Kate will change all that.</abstract>
    
    <byline>Anne Kingston</byline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_ROYALS_PREGFASHION05.jpg"></photo>
 
    <photo.caption>Nothing to see: When she was pregnant with Prince Andrew in 1959, Queen Elizabeth II camouflaged her baby bump with loose coats and suits</photo.caption>
     
  <photo.byline>Central Press/Hulton Archive/Getty</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>The first clue as to how Catherine, duchess of Cambridge, intends to approach her pregnancy, stylistically speaking, was evident days before its sudden, clearly unplanned announcement. Visiting her girlhood alma mater, St. Andrew&rsquo;s School, the princess showed off her field hockey skills with students while wearing a tartan Alexander McQueen coat and high-heeled boots. In retrospect, it indicated that the wife of the future British king plans to accommodate her pregnancy as if she&rsquo;s any other healthy woman expecting a baby with a job to do. </p>
    
    <p>Only, of course, she isn&rsquo;t. The princess faces unique challenges navigating her post-conception world under unprecedented scrutiny. On one hand, she has to appear a relatable, modern mom-to-be; on the other, she&rsquo;s fulfilling an archaic role as the vessel perpetuating the house of Windsor&rsquo;s genetic code. Just as her 2011 wedding to Prince William recalibrated the optics of a British monarchy trying to adapt to the 21st century&mdash;the bride riding in a sleek Rolls-Royce, not a fairy-tale coach; charitable donations requested in lieu of gifts&mdash;so, too, does her pregnancy. </p>
    
    <p>The fact that the royal household was forced to release news of the pregnancy before the princess had safely passed the first trimester reflects awareness of a new reality: that this is the first A-list heir to the British throne born into a post-<em>TMZ </em>world. It was only a matter of time before media jackals, present company included, discovered that the princess had been hospitalized, and so the palace issued a pre-emptive strike. It even named the hospital she was in, knowing that was destined to create a paparazzi encampment outside.  </p>
    
    <p>The palace also shared the sort of private details that would have been unthinkable in previous, more discreet royal generations: the princess was suffering from <em>Hyperemesis gravidarum</em>, a serious condition marked by severe vomiting that can lead to dehydration, kidney failure and even miscarriage, but can also be a marker of twins. Predictably, by day&rsquo;s end, #hypermesisgravidarum was trending on Twitter and bookies were betting on names. </p>
    
    <p>It&rsquo;s a portent of the seven months to come. Kate isn&rsquo;t just giving birth to the next British monarch; she&rsquo;s producing the world&rsquo;s most famous baby in an age in which pregnancy among the rich and famous is a mass-market opiate, with magazines paying hundreds of thousand of dollars for exclusive photos of celebrity spawn.  </p>
    
    <p>Already the princess appears to be bringing British royal maternity into the 20th&mdash;if not 21st&mdash;century. She didn&rsquo;t get pregnant within months of her marriage, as William&rsquo;s mother, Diana, did. Nor is she under the same pressure to produce a male heir, thanks to a commitment to end male primogeniture. Whether a boy or a girl, this child will be third in line to the British throne.  </p>
    
    <p>Mercifully for Kate, royal attitudes to pregnancy have changed over the centuries. Once, doubt over royal paternity could spark revolution, even depose a king, as happened after Mary of Modena, wife of James II, delivered a son in 1688. The king&rsquo;s enemies claimed an imposter infant had been smuggled into the bed in a warming pan after Mary miscarried, and that a false prince had been presented to the people. It wasn&rsquo;t until 1948, just before Prince Charles&rsquo;s birth, that the tradition of ministers of the Crown being present at royal births was discontinued.  </p>
    
    <p>Traditionally, pregnant royals have been neither seen nor heard. Princess Charlotte, the only daughter of George, the prince regent, and later King George IV, was the first pregnant British royal to be immortalized in a formal portrait in 1817. (Her death during childbirth that same year occasioned unprecedented public grief.) No maternity portraits at all exist for Queen Victoria, who bore nine children. Queen Elizabeth II was seen publicly during her pregnancies but was notably absent from regal duty, missing the opening of Parliament, for one.  </p>
    
    <p>Princess Anne, known for her no-nonsense ways, was the first visibly pregnant working royal, carrying out her duties in practical, if dowdy, maternity wear, though that was not until the 1970s. Diana broke with entrenched royal tradition, too, choosing to give birth to her sons in a hospital rather than at home. But she was never a gestation style-setter. While pregnant with William, she favoured blowsy dresses and tent-like coats with bows and Peter Pan collars of the popular variety that used to make pregnant women appear infant-like themselves. It was still a decade until a pregnant Demi Moore proudly posed naked on the cover of <em>Vanity Fair,</em> ushering in the era of maternal clothing designed to celebrate fecundity, not hide it.    </p>
    
    <p>Kate, the most avidly followed royal in history, can&rsquo;t change the part in her hair without triggering reaction. So it&rsquo;s inevitable that her pregnancy&mdash;a period that sees even ordinary women put under the microscope for their behaviour and appearance&mdash;will only amplify attention and her influence. The day the pregnancy was announced, the popular blog <em>What Kate Wore</em> observed that it will put the spotlight on a new generation of British designers, among them Isabella Oliver and Tiffany Rose, who produce maternity clothes.  </p>
    
    <p>Based on Kate&rsquo;s steady fashion track record, it&rsquo;s unlikely that pregnancy will change anything with the exception of her body. Since her marriage, the princess has radiated supermarket-shopping photo-op normalcy. She may have Erdem or Sarah Burton of Alexander McQueen to whip up couture for formal court functions, but she&rsquo;ll likely continue to be seen in mass-market labels&mdash;maternity J Brand jeans and Zara&mdash;along with oversized sweaters from her pre-pregnancy wardrobe, just like most pregnant women.  </p>
    
    <p>Other European queens-to-be have already paved the way in mixing royal with real, namely Princess Mary of Denmark, Princess Victoria of Sweden and Princess M&aacute;xima of the Netherlands. The Danish princess, a mother of four who could be the duchess&rsquo;s sartorial doppelg&auml;nger, was famously photographed for German <em>Vogue </em>in 2011 when pregnant with twins.  </p>
    
    <p>Of course, there&rsquo;s more to consider than fashion choices. When Diana was expecting Prince William, the Queen&rsquo;s press secretary invited Fleet Street editors to Buckingham Palace, where the monarch made a personal appeal to lay off the royal family, especially the pregnant Diana. This week&rsquo;s announcement is a similar salvo, telegraphing that the princess&rsquo;s health is fragile and to back off. It&rsquo;s a reminder that though Kate is bound to be a pregnancy trailblazer, if she wants some semblance of a private life, she may go back to a time-tested tactic for royal moms-to-be: to disappear. The couple has already cancelled several appearances. Knowing what we know, who would blame them? </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Royal Baby</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Is the future heir fair game?</hedline>
    
    <abstract>The findings of the Leveson inquiry may alter coverage of the most anticipated baby since William himself</abstract>
    
    <byline>Rosemary Westwood</byline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_ROYALS_LEVENSON02.jpg"></photo>
 
    <photo.caption>Boundaries: The U.K. press has been more restrained in the new era of media regulation</photo.caption>
 
  <photo.byline>Alastair Grant/AP</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>As soon as the royal baby story hit the wires, up popped the &ldquo;live coverage&rdquo; feeds on the <em>Guardian</em> and<em> Telegraph</em> news sites. </p>
    
    <p>It&rsquo;s the &ldquo;only story that anybody on the royal beat is going to be working on for the next nine months,&rdquo; declared the<em> Telegraph</em>&rsquo;s Gordon Rayner. He predicted &ldquo;feverish&rdquo; coverage of the pregnancy before pronouncing it &ldquo;the most anticipated baby since Prince William himself.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>But even as reporters and camera crews huddled outside the hospital where Kate was being treated for extreme morning sickness, anxious for more news (William leaving the building was about as dramatic as it got), British MPs were busy debating a controversial plan to reel in the more zealous members of the press. </p>
    
    <p>The Leveson report calls for greater scrutiny of the media through a new independent regulatory body, backed up by legislation. It stems from the Leveson inquiry, the government&rsquo;s response to the British phone-hacking scandal. Prime Minister David Cameron has welcomed the idea of a low-cost body to handle libel disputes, levy fines and even demand apologies. But, wary of too much legislative meddling, he dumped the file onto the desks of Fleet Street editors. Come up with a plan, he warned them, or expect a new press law. </p>
    
    <p>Into this &ldquo;new era&rdquo; of press regulation drops a royal baby. &ldquo;Clearly the whole political background will have an impact on how this pregnancy is covered,&rdquo; said Richard Palmer, royal correspondent for the <em>Daily Express</em>.  </p>
    
    <p>The royal family and the phone-hacking scandal are inextricably linked. In 2007, the royal editor of the now defunct <em>News of the World</em> and a private investigator employed by the paper became the first people convicted and jailed for phone hacking after they intercepted the messages of members of the royal household. </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;The press has been more restrained partly because of the political climate here regarding the press and intrusion and privacy issues,&rdquo; Palmer said. </p>
    
    <p>But the public&rsquo;s appetite for royal baby news hovers around the all-you-can-eat level, and the story marks a commercial conundrum. &ldquo;There are topless pictures of the duchess of Cambridge published, and the reaction is: &lsquo;This is outrageous. Where can I see those pictures?&rsquo; &rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>As the elder son of Diana, princess of Wales, prepares for fatherhood, the British press is still &ldquo;tarred with the brush of 15 or 20 years ago,&rdquo; Palmer noted. &ldquo;What&rsquo;s stronger is a fear of the backlash from readers if your paper goes too far in this coverage, and that&rsquo;s where Diana comes back into play. If any paper was perceived by the public to be doing what they did to Diana, that could have a negative impact on sales figures.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>The Queen&rsquo;s former PR man said that so far, the press has used restraint. &ldquo;Yes, they&rsquo;re outside the hospital, but there is nothing to say and there is nothing to photograph,&rdquo; said Dickie Arbiter, who was press spokesperson for the Queen until 2000. With the parade of morning-sickness experts and rumours of twins, the media is &ldquo;pumping it up a bit.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;They&rsquo;re looking for a story, because there isn&rsquo;t one.&rdquo; (Aside from the fact that a new heir to the throne has been conceived.) &ldquo;I think the media have gone easy,&rdquo; he added. &ldquo;They&rsquo;re not intruding whatsoever.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>These, then, appear to be the &ldquo;new&rdquo; boundaries for Britain&rsquo;s press: feel free to set up camp outside the hospital, just don&rsquo;t walk inside, notebook hidden in a white coat, hoping to be confused for a doctor.  </p>
    
    <p>If and when a pregnant Kate makes a public appearance, she must expect clicking cameras. &ldquo;All other times, she is entitled to her privacy,&rdquo; said Arbiter, &ldquo;and I think she&rsquo;s going to get it.&rdquo;   </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>TV</sections>
    
  <body.head>
    <hedline>Serial storytelling</hedline>
    
    <abstract>Successful TV dramas are unfolding one episode at a time, and procedurals are taking notes</abstract>
    
    <byline>Jaime J. Weinman</byline>
  </body.head>
    
     <photo href="file://images/MAC50_PROCEDURALSMERGE.jpg"></photo>

  <photo.caption>Continuity: Law &amp; Order may win in syndication, but serialized shows like Homeland and The Walking Dead pull in the ratings</photo.caption>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>We used to know a TV story was almost over when there were only 10 minutes left in the episode. Today most shows aren&rsquo;t over until the series is cancelled. The serialized drama, where stories unfold over multiple instalments, was once mostly confined to soap operas, but serials like the Showtime cable series <em>Homeland </em>are increasingly winning the awards. And times aren&rsquo;t so great for the procedural, the TV form where every episode is a self-contained story, usually a crime that gets solved. &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t think there&rsquo;s any question that any writer would prefer to write serialized stories,&rdquo; says Hart Hanson, a Canadian TV writer and creator of the successful procedural <em>Bones</em>. TV critic Alan Sepinwall, whose new book <em>The Revolution Was Televised</em> is an inside look at the best TV dramas of the last 15 years, puts it more bluntly: &ldquo;Procedurals are still by and large designed for people who don&rsquo;t want to have to think too hard, or watch every episode.&rdquo;  </p>
    
    <p>These days it&rsquo;s often the more complicated serials that pull in the ratings. The biggest hit dramas on cable are AMC&rsquo;s serialized zombie adventure <em>The Walking Dead</em>, which pulled in 10 million viewers for its season premiere, and FX&rsquo;s equally serialized biker drama <em>Sons of Anarchy</em>. The only new drama this fall with high ratings is NBC&rsquo;s serial <em>Revolution</em>, whose premiere attracted 11 million viewers interested in a world where the power has gone out and no one knows who did it or why it happened. There hasn&rsquo;t been a breakout procedural hit in several years, which may explain why networks are starting to move away from that form. The USA network&rsquo;s <em>Burn Notice</em>, a popular adventure show about a former secret agent, used to focus on weekly adventures where the hero helped ordinary people fight mob bosses or drug dealers. The creator, Matt Nix, told the <em>Hollywood Reporter</em> that he recently switched &ldquo;from a largely self-contained, episodic show into a highly serialized drama.&rdquo; And it worked: the ratings have gone up now that more episodes end on cliffhangers. </p>
    
    <p>And serialized drama is now considered the artistic pinnacle of television. All the shows in Sepinwall&rsquo;s book are serials, such as <em>Friday Night Lights,</em> and only one of them&mdash;<em>Buffy the Vampire Slayer</em>&mdash;did any stand-alone &ldquo;monster-of-the-week&rdquo; episodes where bad guys were introduced and killed off in one hour. In doing interviews for the book, Sepinwall found writers were relieved by &ldquo;the lack of narrative rules&rdquo; HBO imposed on shows like <em>The Wire</em>, where creator David Simon &ldquo;didn&rsquo;t bother with episodic stories at all,&rdquo; treating the series as a novel for TV.  </p>
    
    <p>Writers of episodic shows, even hits like the <em>CSI</em> franchise or <em>House,</em> often envy the freedom of open-ended dramas. Hanson says a serial has &ldquo;more time to stretch out and do a proper job, more subtle story beats and shifts and dynamics, more opportunity for characters to affect action.&rdquo; And a procedural, where characters solve more mysteries than most cops do in a lifetime, has trouble being realistic. &ldquo;Neatly solving a case each week propels the entire tone of the series away from naturalistic drama,&rdquo; Hanson says. &ldquo;Somehow, within the fabric of the series, we have to create a universe in which it isn&rsquo;t insane to catch a murderer over, say, three story days.&rdquo;  </p>
    
    <p>But if procedurals don&rsquo;t have the flexibility of a show like HBO&rsquo;s <em>The Wire</em>, they&rsquo;ve still been learning from serials, throwing in hints of continuity to tease the viewers. &ldquo;Today&rsquo;s procedurals seem to feature more ongoing elements,&rdquo; says Sepinwall, pointing to shows like ABC&rsquo;s C<em>astle</em>, where the female lead spent years trying to crack the case of her mother&rsquo;s murder. Aidan Quinn, who plays a police officer on the procedural <em>Elementary</em>, says the writers write in hints about the past lives of characters: during an early show, &ldquo;one of the producers dropped a piece of information to me about upcoming episodes. I said, &lsquo;I&rsquo;m glad you told me that, because that affects how I play the rest of the scenes in this episode.&rsquo; &rdquo; Compared to a show like <em>Star Trek</em>, where no one remembered anything that happened in previous episodes, old-fashioned shows like <em>Elementary</em> or <em>NCIS</em> are at least somewhat serialized. </p>
    
    <p>One reason is that serialization attracts the most devoted fans. Hanson says a portion of the <em>Bones</em> audience watches the show to see a murder solved every week, and the writers have to make sure to keep that element of the show. But &ldquo;the remarkable loyalty of our audience, over eight seasons, is because of the serial elements,&rdquo; especially the romance between the two lead characters. &ldquo;If our cases are highly compressed,&rdquo; he adds, &ldquo;we compensate in our relationship arcs. We may catch a murderer in 44 minutes, but it took us six years to have Booth and Brennan consummate their love.&rdquo; Fans are particularly fascinated by long romance arcs. Krystin Pellerin, a regular on the CBC procedural <em>Republic of Doyle</em>, says what fans talk most about is whether her character will get together with the male lead, Jake: &ldquo;Some people are just coming up and giving Leslie advice on what to do about Jake, that she should tell him where to go, or give him a break.&rdquo; Solving a mystery is fun for newcomers, but regular viewers argue about whether the characters will die or get married. </p>
    
    <p>With all these things pushing TV in the direction of more serialization, is there any hope for the survival of the stand-alone episode? Hanson thinks they still have a place on shows that are seeking a larger audience than the average cable show: &ldquo;A serialized show has a tougher time picking up new viewers because people think they&rsquo;ve missed the bus.&rdquo; And the less serialized a show is, the better it does in syndication, where episodes are frequently shown out of order and where viewers don&rsquo;t always come in knowing what happened in previous instalments. A show like <em>Law &amp; Order</em>, with almost no ongoing stories, is still a major success in syndication, while serials like <em>Lost</em> or <em>Breaking Bad</em> can&rsquo;t make much money in daily reruns.  </p>
    
    <p>But even that business model may be changing, since new media is opening up new ways for serialized shows to make a profit. Shows like <em>Mad Men</em> have been so successful on Netflix that the streaming service has created its own morally ambiguous serialized drama, the Kevin Spacey vehicle <em>House of Cards</em>, which will have its premiere in January. And thanks to streaming, DVR playback and complete seasons on DVD, viewers can easily catch up on past instalments of a serialized show, which may make it unnecessary to market TV shows to people who haven&rsquo;t seen previous episodes. </p>
    
    <p>Of course, as it becomes more common, the formulas of serialized drama could become as worn out as the old system of wrapping up every story in an hour. Fans of ongoing stories sometimes get angry with how much they&rsquo;re stretched out. &ldquo;It frustrates the audience when they can&rsquo;t see whether something is going to happen or not,&rdquo; says H&eacute;l&egrave;ne Joy of <em>Murdoch Mysteries</em>, another procedural that became more serialized as it went along. In the 2000s, some serial dramas annoyed viewers by dragging out story arcs and mysteries: fans spent years speculating about the solution to the mysteries of <em>Lost</em>, only to feel a sense of anticlimax when the series left many of these questions unresolved and ended with all the characters meeting up in a blissful New Age afterlife. Some shows deal with this problem by churning through a lot of story material very fast. <em>Homeland</em>, which won the Emmy for best drama series last year, surprised many fans by wrapping up an important story arc&mdash;the heroine&rsquo;s attempt to have the male lead arrested as a suspected terrorist&mdash;early in the second season; that kind of speed may be the only way for a serial to avoid exhausting storylines. </p>
    
    <p>Sometimes it helps to create stories unconnected to the main arc: fans of <em>The X-Files</em> often preferred the stand-alone episodes to the ones dealing with the over-arching alien conspiracy, and Sepinwall says that on <em>Buffy the Vampire Slayer</em>, the writers benefited from their ability &ldquo;to move back and forth and just do monster-of-the-week stuff when needed so they wouldn&rsquo;t be burned out by the 22nd episode.&rdquo; It could be that if the stand-alone, case-of-the-week episode survives, it&rsquo;ll be because audiences need something to keep them from getting bored with never-ending story arcs on serials. But for now, at least, fans may be more interested in figuring out what&rsquo;s going to happen in future episodes, not analyzing the plot of the episode they just saw. &ldquo;Any time we make a shift in our characters&rsquo; relationship, there is a great hue and cry,&rdquo; explains Hanson. &ldquo;We&rsquo;ve come to realize that we fear silence much more than cursing. We never hear any cursing about the weekly crime story.&rdquo;     </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Web</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
    <hedline>Getting to know you</hedline>
    
    <abstract>A social experiment in Calgary is building bridges between disparate social groups</abstract>
    
    <byline>Anthony A. Davis</byline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_WESHOULDKNOW01.jpg"></photo>
  
    <photo.caption>Sociable: Mark Hopkins relied on email, a website and Facebook to lure these strangers to his apartment one recent Sunday&mdash;to talk to each other </photo.caption>
 
  <photo.byline>Photograph by Todd Korol</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>The results of Mark Hopkins&rsquo;s social experiment are posted on his wall&mdash;a real wall, the one by his front door. Hundreds of coloured name tags are plastered there, just a fraction of the 1,600 strangers he has invited to his Calgary apartment over the last four years for company, conversation, and philosophical duels. Among the guests were Naheed Nenshi, before he was mayor, and Alison Redford, before she was premier. </p>
    
    <p>Tall, gangly, ruddy-cheeked and boyish, the former bashful wallflower has bloomed into social impresario. &ldquo;In elementary school, I was the kid you&rsquo;d see sitting alone on the step, reading a book, eating his apple,&rdquo; says Hopkins, whose father was a database consultant and his mother a marine biologist. Then, in Grade 12, &ldquo;a switch flipped&rdquo; and the extrovert emerged. </p>
    
    <p>Every second Sunday since 2008, Hopkins has hosted what he calls a &ldquo;We should know each other&rdquo; party. Using an email list, a Facebook page and his website <em>WSKEO.com</em>, he invites anyone and everyone to his unprepossessing apartment in a brick walk-up across from Calgary&rsquo;s glass-and-steel downtown. </p>
    
    <p>One recent Sunday, 15 people filled the worn sofas and chairs, chatter criss-crossing the room like verbal confetti. There was talk of the presidential debates on one couch. Problems with psychiatry&rsquo;s <em>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</em> on the other. There&rsquo;s never a theme, and viewpoints clash. &ldquo;I personally get excited when voices get raised a little bit. But nothing has ever gotten out of hand.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Hopkins&rsquo;s goal is to chip away at the socio-economic, ethnic, occupational and ideological barriers that define our social zones. </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;We all exist in these silos that consist of our school friends, family, industry friends, peer groups. That kind of thing can be limiting,&rdquo; says Hopkins, co-artistic director of Swallow-a-Bicycle, a fringe-theatre company known for staging plays in offbeat locations. He&rsquo;s also associate producer for the One Yellow Rabbit performance theatre. </p>
    
    <p>Realizing he was too cloistered in the theatrical crowd, Hopkins decided to construct a societal bridge in Calgary, one that would bring plumber together with politician, actor with accountant.  </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;I didn&rsquo;t realize that I had preconceptions about politicians or police of&#64257;cers until I started meeting them. Lawyers, too. Coming from an arts background, I certainly had perceptions about them that were largely incorrect.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>To recognize his leadership and cultural contribution to the city, Conservative MP Michelle Rempel (Calgary Centre-North) nominated Hopkins for a Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee medal, which was awarded in October. An alumnus of the &ldquo;We should know each other&rdquo; parties, Rempel was always welcomed, even though many of the guests were left-leaning. </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;Part of that is Mark. He&rsquo;s set a tone of, &lsquo;We are going to build community.&rsquo; But just because I&rsquo;m a conservative politician doesn&rsquo;t mean I don&rsquo;t have a lot of friends in the arts community,&rdquo; says the MP, a pianist who once considered a career in music. </p>
    
    <p>Hopkins often refers to a book by American political scientist Robert D. Putnam, <em>Bowling Alone: The Collapse and Revival of American Community</em>, where the author describes two kinds of social capital. Bonding capital occurs when you socialize with people who are like you in age, ethnicity, economic status, and religion. Bridging capital happens when you befriend people unlike you. Without bridging capital, Putnam suggests civic tension grows and quality of life declines. </p>
    
    <p>Karen Ross, 29, moved last September from Vancouver to work on her Ph.D. in counselling psychology at the University of Calgary. She met Hopkins at a local pub and has attended two parties. &ldquo;You kind of have to go in with no expectations about whether you&rsquo;ll like people, or whether they&rsquo;ll be intriguing or superficial or crazy,&rdquo; she says. &ldquo;You get a chance to see how you navigate this series of ambiguous social interactions where you aren&rsquo;t primed with much information about the person you&rsquo;re talking to.&rdquo; Sometimes, she adds, &ldquo;you have really, really lovely and resonant conversations.&rdquo;   </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Film</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
    <hedline>Rated A for adultery</hedline>
    
    <abstract>Cheating moves from today&rsquo;s headlines into tomorrow&rsquo;s plots on the big screen</abstract>
    
    <byline>Brian D. Johnson</byline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_ADULTERY01.jpg"></photo>
  <photo.caption>&lsquo;A Royal Affair&rsquo;: A new crop of films about infidelity display empathy and affection for the lovers, even if their betrayals cause ruin or death</photo.caption>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>If David Petraeus is seeking to escape his marital woes at the multiplex this month, he&rsquo;ll have to choose carefully. Best to steer clear of <em>Anna Karenina</em>. It&rsquo;s the season&rsquo;s most exquisite costume drama, and Keira Knightley has never looked lovelier, but it&rsquo;s still the story of an affair that turns into a train wreck. Petraeus, who resigned as CIA director over an extramarital romance, may also want to avoid <em>Hyde Park on Hudson</em>. This light confection about president Franklin Delano Roosevelt entertaining British royalty may seem harmless, but FDR&rsquo;s knack for blithely cheating on his wife without missing a beat would make a modern philanderer envious. If Petraeus hopes to soothe his soul with a cathartic blast of Beethoven,<em> A Late Quartet</em> may look like just the ticket. But not so fast: it&rsquo;s about a famous string quartet that becomes unstrung by one member&rsquo;s affair and another&rsquo;s adulterous fling. Even 18th-century Copenhagen is not a safe escape. In<em> A Royal Affair</em>, Denmark&rsquo;s queen betrays her king with his doctor, a heroic civil servant whose free-thinking behaviour costs him his head. </p>
    
    <p>The holiday movie season is awash with sobering tales of adultery in high places. In each of these four films, sexual betrayal results in someone getting hurt, if not killed, but the cheating lovers are portrayed with glowing empathy and affection. Even if they&rsquo;ve doomed themselves by following their desires, they seem nobler for it&mdash;true to their passion, if not to their mates. </p>
    
    <p>In <em>Hyde Park on Hudson</em> and <em>A Royal Affair</em>, infidelity is complicated by affairs of state. In 1939, on the eve of the Second World War, FDR is preparing to host the first visit of a reigning British monarch to America at his country home in upstate New York when he strikes up an affair with his distant cousin, Margaret &ldquo;Daisy&rdquo; Suckley (Laura Linney). Portrayed with cavalier charm by Bill Murray, Roosevelt is a benign womanizer who can take anything in stride, even though he was crippled by childhood polio. </p>
    
    <p>His tryst with Daisy begins as an old friendship rekindled with benefits. But from its indecorous debut, he&rsquo;s the one reaping the benefits. Daisy comes to realize she&rsquo;s just FDR&rsquo;s latest distraction, like another specimen in his stamp collection. The forlorn mistress is further marginalized as the story&rsquo;s axis shifts to the fish-out-of-water comedy of the discombobulated King George VI and Queen Elizabeth being served hot dogs at a presidential picnic. Murray&rsquo;s Roosevelt emerges untarnished, displaying an avuncular grace likely to turn Oscar&rsquo;s head. </p>
    
    <p><em>A Royal Affair</em>, Denmark&rsquo;s submission for Best Foreign Language Film, presents a more dire scenario of dangerous liaisons&mdash;a turning point in Danish history where romance and politics combust on a Shakespearean scale. It&rsquo;s the late 1700s, and Denmark is ruled by the spoiled and petulant King Christian VII (Mikkel Boe F&oslash;lsgaard), who plays the fool and spends his nights in brothels while his courtiers run a corrupt feudal regime and his wife suffers from neglect. The king finds an unlikely soulmate in Johann Struensee (Mads Mikkelssen), a dashing German doctor committed to the reformist ideals of the Enlightenment. As Struensee becomes the king&rsquo;s personal physician, then the power behind the throne, he also warms the bed of Christian&rsquo;s queen (Alicia Vikander). </p>
    
    <p>The king is a bratty halfwit obsessed with <em>Hamlet</em> and, like Shakespeare&rsquo;s Danish prince, his madness is half-real, half-fake. But he&rsquo;s a pathetic figure, and so abusive to his wife that when his new best friend cuckolds him, he&rsquo;s hardly a victim. Struensee is the tragic hero. As the doctor risks his neck to liberate both Denmark&rsquo;s queen and its serfs, it would be hard to find a worthier case of betrayal. Yet by conducting an affair while attempting to serve as his country&rsquo;s political saviour, Struensee seals his fate. It makes you wonder why such a sterling leader, like a Petraeus or a Bill Clinton, is willing to invite ruin by trying to have it all. </p>
    
    <p>On second thought, maybe Petraeus could find some solace in <em>A Royal Affair</em>. It may be vindicating to place himself in a long line of fallen romantic heroes infamous for adultery, though he might want to slip into the darkened cinema solo.     </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Taste</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
    <hedline>A continental divide over a midday meal</hedline>
    
    <abstract>Sunday lunch is laid-back and luxurious; brunch is fast and furious</abstract>
    
    <byline>Pamela Cuthbert</byline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_SUNDAYLUNCH01.jpg"></photo>
 
    <photo.caption>Slow food: At Edulis in Toronto, Michael Caballo and Tobey Nemeth serve Sunday lunch, a multi-course, set menu made for sharing</photo.caption>
 
  <photo.byline>Photograph by Jenna Marie Wakani</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Sunday lunch versus Sunday brunch: the difference is only a few letters, but the two are opposite approaches to the midday meal. Brunch, a North American invention, was initially about time&mdash;not quite breakfast, not quite lunch&mdash;but has evolved into a loud, fast-paced antidote to a hangover in which friends down cocktails and dine on dishes like deep-fried French toast. Sunday lunch, a European tradition, is a slow and sumptuous feast that involves family, many courses of finely crafted dishes, some wine and time for dessert. And though brunch dominates in Canada, at least one Toronto restaurant is trying to make Sunday lunch an occasion. </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;Brunch is about business, it&rsquo;s not about joy,&rdquo; says Tobey Nemeth, who runs the small bistro Edulis with her husband, chef Michael Caballo. After a few years spent cooking around the world, they took over the space earlier this year. &ldquo;Sunday lunch was one of the first things we set out to do,&rdquo; Caballo says. </p>
    
    <p>The $40 set menu encourages lingering over dishes that range from fish mousse to braised rabbit, garlicky potatoes and rich pies. There is only one seating, so the table is yours from noon to 3 p.m. Dishes are family-style, which means shared platters of food. To slow things down, wine by the bottle is half-price. </p>
    
    <p>The inspiration came in part from Caballo&rsquo;s childhood in Edmonton where, every Sunday after church, the community hall would be packed with a couple hundred hungry diners. &ldquo;It was a sit-down lunch of probably seven courses with mostly Italian families, affordable and very delicious,&rdquo; he says. Time spent abroad, particularly in Italy and Spain, sparked the idea to offer the menu at Edulis. &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve never seen brunch offered in Italy,&rdquo; says Caballo. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s not part of their culture.&rdquo; Years of working the brunch grind, an experience he sums up as &ldquo;brutal,&rdquo; was also motivation. </p>
    
    <p>Still, some high-end chefs are attracted to the frenetic pace of brunch and the freedom it offers from the strictures of dinner service. In Toronto, chef Victor Barry, known for his exacting standards at Splendido restaurant, started brunch&mdash;his first&mdash;last year at his casual eatery The County General. With just 27 seats, they sometimes sell as many as 180 meals in a few hours. &ldquo;Sunday brunch is absolutely bats--t crazy,&rdquo; says Barry. &ldquo;I love it.&rdquo; He also cooks for the crowds who expect standard fare. &ldquo;Torontonians love their eggs with brunch and they&rsquo;re easy to please. We keep Springsteen blasting and everyone&rsquo;s happy.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Sinclair Philip, co-owner of Vancouver Island&rsquo;s Sooke Harbour House, about 40 km west of Victoria, has steered clear of brunch for more than 30 years. A cornerstone of the midday weekend meal is the calibre of dishes, he explains. At Sooke, there might be one egg-related dish such as quiche, but the focus is on soups, seasonal salads and mains with fresh fish and seafood. Desserts are popular, as they are at Edulis, where parties of six or more are often served their own cake.  </p>
    
    <p>Initially, Sunday lunch proved a hard sell at Edulis. &ldquo;We stuck it out those first months,&rdquo; says Caballo, recalling a room half-full at best. Since a rave review earlier this fall, they now book tables a week or two in advance. &ldquo;At first, people didn&rsquo;t really get the set menu,&rdquo; says Nemeth. &ldquo;In Europe it&rsquo;s standard, but here it&rsquo;s hard for people to accept they&rsquo;re not in charge.&rdquo; The number of requests for substitutions has dropped off significantly. &ldquo;The list of allergies and requests can be encyclopedic at dinner, but with lunch we get very, very few. There&rsquo;s something about yielding to us.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Barry says that though Sunday brunch is a lot of fun, &ldquo;Most people look at it as something that fulfills a need.&rdquo; Sunday lunch, on the other hand, inspires nostalgia&nbsp;in diners such as Josh Josephson, a well-travelled gourmand and owner of The Cookbook Store in Toronto. &ldquo;Enjoying some good wine during this meal on a leisurely, sunny Sunday afternoon was like a weekend holiday in some ways,&rdquo; he says of dining at Edulis. At Sooke Harbour House, Philip feels the same. &ldquo;A lot of Italians go to the countryside and have lunch on Sundays with friends and family. Here, it&rsquo;s the same thing. People get out of town and just relax.&rdquo; </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <body.head>
    <hedline>That famous artist who drew New York</hedline>
    
    <abstract>Plus, a man who was wrong about most everything, an ode to the Christmas tree, the horrors and absurdities of Israel&rsquo;s state of perma-war, and John Lennon&rsquo;s letters</abstract>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_BOOKS06.jpg"></photo>
  <photo.caption>&lsquo;Saul Steinberg&rsquo;: A major new biography illuminates the life and fascinating artwork of the clever, sophisticated, difficult New Yorker</photo.caption>
    
  <photo.byline>Gjon Mili/GETTY IMAGES</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
  
    <p><em>SAUL STEINBERG:  A BIOGRAPHY</em> </p>
    
    <p>Deirdre Bair </p>
    
    <p>Lion-headed men in Brooks Brothers suits. Ladies with lipstick-slashed mouths and stilettos on gams that go up to their necks. A swirly typographical landscape of question marks. A confident 5 (male) and a dejected 2 (female) wonder how they can possibly be a good fit. </p>
    
    <p>Saul Steinberg&rsquo;s illustrations are among the most identifiable artworks of our age, at once puzzling and fascinating. His most famous image, <em>View of the World From 9th Avenue</em>, the cover of <em>The New Yorker</em> on March 29, 1976, has been endlessly adapted for other jurisdictions, and no wonder. It is a delight, and looks so simple: even if you have no artistic bent, it makes you want to grab a bottle of India ink and create your own Steinbergian &ldquo;autogeography.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Now, 13 years after Steinberg&rsquo;s death, cultural biographer Deirdre Bair has produced a monumental study that illuminates this clever, sophisticated, difficult, intensely sociable but elusive New Yorker. It took her four years, and it wasn&rsquo;t clear sailing: the Saul Steinberg Foundation allowed her to use only 35 of his images; a pity that, because readers of this first major biography would rather feast on his work than have it described in words, no matter how ably stitched together. </p>
    
    <p>Bair tells her subject&rsquo;s story well: the emotional effect of leaving his native Romania for Milan to study architecture, then, as a result of Mussolini&rsquo;s racial laws, being uprooted from his new home and transplanted to the U.S. He travelled widely but was indelibly attached to New York, the locus of success, money and intellectual sustenance. </p>
    
    <p>And women. During his 85 years, he loved three and was chronically unfaithful to them all, yet remained close to each. When he died, his wife, Hedda Sterne, was holding his hand. They had been separated for 40 years.  </p>
    
    <p>Steinberg got the fame he wanted and a place in the history of art all his own. As he explained it, &ldquo;I am the writer who draws.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <byline>Sarah Murdoch</byline> 
    
    
    <p><em>A MAN OF MISCONCEPTIONS: THE LIFE OF AN ECCENTRIC  IN AN AGE OF CHANGE</em> </p>
    
    <p>John Glassie </p>
    
    <p>Athanasius Kircher of Fulda (c. 1601-1680) occupies a strange niche in intellectual history. Kircher, a German Jesuit who founded a museum of curiosities and wonders in Rome, pops up in the early, confused history of dozens of scientific disciplines, from acoustics to geology to sinology. He was one of the most famous and prolific scholars in Europe, yet his library-filling oeuvre has left no trace of value. He has  recently become a favourite among students of early-modern weirdness, evolving from being forgotten to being remembered for being forgotten. </p>
    
    <p>John Glassie&rsquo;s affectionate portrait accounts for much about this man&rsquo;s evaporating importance. Father Kircher was wrong about most everything he turned his mind to, and when he was right it was mostly dumb luck. As a student of Egyptian hieroglyphics, for example, he had the good sense to suspect that the contemporary Coptic language of Egypt might provide clues to the lingo of Pharaonic Egypt. But while this hint would be used in the 19th century to help crack hieroglyphics, Kircher squandered it, improvising hundreds of pages of worthless but attention-grabbing &ldquo;translations.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>His greatest contemporaries saw through Kircher: the Dutch physicist Christiaan Huygens called his work &ldquo;the nonsense of fools,&rdquo; and Ren&eacute; Descartes agreed the Jesuit was &ldquo;more of a charlatan than a scholar.&rdquo; Kircher was indeed a congenital exaggerator, full of fun but ludicrous tales about his own life (which Glassie obligingly explores). Regrettably, he wasn&rsquo;t much of an experimenter, he was gullible about the exaggerations of others and he never did get a handle on cutting-edge math. Although Kircher had his defenders, the learned world eventually came to agree with Huygens and Descartes, imparting a rather sad ending to Glassie&rsquo;s story of an extraordinary life.</p>
    
     <byline>Colby Cosh</byline>
   
    
    <p><em>INVENTING THE  CHRISTMAS TREE</em> </p>
    
    <p>Bernd Brunner </p>
    
    <p>This slim and beautifully illustrated tome is less a history&mdash;Brunner cheerfully admits to his subject&rsquo;s murky origins&mdash;than an ode to the Christmas tree&rsquo;s astonishing and continuing evolution. It&rsquo;s one thing to find sparse references to the tree within the records of medieval German guilds&mdash;the Freiburg Fraternity of Baker&rsquo;s Apprentices seems to have had one up, complete with apples, gingerbread and tinsel, as early as 1419&mdash;and quite another to see an unmistakable Christmas tree in a Japanese print from 1920. In it, a traditionally dressed family eats Japanese food in front of this weird-but-cool foreign thing, hung with origami, lights and paper fans. </p>
    
    <p>It&rsquo;s hardly surprising that the Christmas tree&rsquo;s more ancient roots grew among the German guilds&mdash;close-knit associations that had money, common indoor space, traditions of communal celebrations and (crucially) nearby coniferous forests. It was a much slower, and occasionally resisted, process to bring it into private houses. First, those homes had to get bigger, and the German upper classes obliged in the 18th century with houses containing purpose-built rooms, like parlours, suitable for family trees. The less well-off responded by hanging their trees, sometimes upside down, from the ceilings of their smaller dwellings, a practice still followed in some German churches. </p>
    
    <p>Even as the tree left its native land with German migration (or by high-level marriage: it was the union of Queen Victoria and Prince Albert that brought the Christmas tree to Britain, where Dickens greeted it as &ldquo;a pretty German toy&rdquo;), some traditionalists hesitated. Catholics, focused on the manger tableau, objected to what they saw as the pagan elements of the Lutherans&rsquo; &ldquo;Tannenbaum religion,&rdquo; a feeling shared by the American descendants of strict Calvinists: &ldquo;The Puritan blood still flows too briskly in my veins,&rdquo; wrote New Englander Lydia Maria Child in 1845, &ldquo;to allow me to relish over much the Christmas tree.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>But there&rsquo;s something about a light-draped tree, and resistance was hopeless. Throughout the West, homes sport mangers <em>and</em> trees, while the &ldquo;tree&rdquo; erected in an Abu Dhabi hotel lobby in 2010&mdash;a gold- and gem-studded, 10-m monument to conspicuous consumption&mdash;shows the extent of the Christmas tree&rsquo;s worldwide conquest.</p>
    
     <byline>Brian Bethune</byline> 
     
     
    
    <p><em>THE PEOPLE OF FOREVER  ARE NOT AFRAID</em> </p>
    
    <p>Shani Boianjiu </p>
    
    <p>Israeli teenagers aren&rsquo;t so different. They bemoan the lack of places to host unsupervised parties. They complain about cellphone reception that musters &ldquo;two bars for, like, 10 seconds.&rdquo; They daydream about their friend&rsquo;s older brother. But then&mdash;then they join the army to prepare for war, and their boyfriends start getting killed. Boianjiu, Israel&rsquo;s 25-year-old fiction wunderkind, has written a spectacular first book. It follows three friends from their sleepy settler town through their years of rather inglorious military service and on to their wobbly landing as civilians. </p>
    
    <p>Boianjiu&rsquo;s plot covers a lot of ground, maybe too much, on the margins of a militarized society, including the plight of Sudanese refugees and trafficked sex workers, a queasy abortion and matter-of-fact military rape. The unrepentantly political book tends toward unsparing criticism of the moral decay of Israeli society. One character, watching another unspool in the wake of her military service, offers the following consolation: &ldquo;It&rsquo;s not you. It&rsquo;s this f--ked-up army; it f--ks you up.&rdquo; Hence the ability of an otherwise normal person to look at a nearby stranger, imagine a suicide bomber and resign herself to a fiery death. One mordant soldier notes that Israel opens its borders just enough to allow Palestinians to build Israeli houses cheaply, but not enough to respect their dignity. Yet what may look absurd and untenable has become normalized: thus can a sardonic checkpoint officer detain a Palestinian child knowing that an &ldquo;arrest of a child was always at least page five.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>The book&rsquo;s tone distinguishes it, elevating youthful musings to the vicinity of high art. The emphatically young and irreverent voices of three Israeli women, alive to the horrors and absurdities of Israel&rsquo;s state of perma-war, animate this unmistakably serious and ambitious novel. Its characters face the problem of &ldquo;the future of the past,&rdquo; bearing the weight of their unwanted experiences. They emerge not quite wise, not quite nihilists, and all too rapidly, young no more. </p>
    
    <byline>Andrew Stobo Sniderman </byline>
  
    
   <p><em>THE JOHN LENNON LETTERS </em></p>
   
   
    <p>Edited and with an Introduction by Hunter Davies </p>
    
    <p>Just when you thought the last scrap had been scavenged from the Beatles&rsquo; apple, along comes this compendium of Lennon&rsquo;s missives, postcards, autographs and, yes, shopping lists. Surely, as George Harrison once sang, it&rsquo;s all too much? </p>
    
    <p>Well, not quite. Thirty-two years after his death, the Lennon that most of us think we know is a rock &rsquo;n&rsquo; roll myth, and this handsome tome helps to humanize him. Davies, authorized Beatles biographer and Lennon confidant, has gathered 286 personal documents, most of which are reproduced in colour. Some are typed&mdash;badly, with apologies&mdash;but the majority are handwritten, and illustrated by comic doodles. Having studied art, and being an avowed disciple of <em>The Goon Show</em>&rsquo;s surreal comic genius Spike Milligan, Lennon infused nearly all of his correspondence with a manic creativity and visual flair. One can read the letters in their transcribed versions by Davies, but it&rsquo;s more fun to pore over the originals. </p>
    
    <p>Granted, Lennon could be ornery (to correspondents he perceived as didactic), defensive (to critics of work by his wife, Yoko Ono), cavalier (to relatives who brought up his faults), sententious (to anyone who asked him about the Maharishi Mahesh Yogi) and, occasionally, downright nasty&mdash;especially in letters to Paul McCartney that now read like fleshed-out versions of celebrity Twitter spats. Nonetheless, he&rsquo;d sign most notes with &ldquo;love&rdquo; and a drawing, and always offer a genuine bit of himself. </p>
    
    <p>Many of these documents are addressed to fans whose letters he would apparently randomly pick out of massive piles of fan mail. His direct engagement with their questions shows a rare generosity of spirit. This is why it&rsquo;s heartbreaking to see Lennon&rsquo;s inscription on a copy of<em> The Catcher in the Rye</em>, signed for his assassin just hours before Mark David Chapman shot him. We all know his sudden death was a terrible artistic loss, but this book makes it clear, more than ever, how lamentable it is that we lost Lennon the man. </p>
    
    <byline>Mike Doherty</byline>
  
    
  <p><em>Maclean&rsquo;s</em> top 20 books of 2012</p>
  
  <p>Here are the books we really loved this year</p>
    
 
    <p>Non-fiction </p>
    
    <p><em>Leonardo And The Last Supper</em> Ross King  </p>
    <p>An enthralling take on the &ldquo;subtle feints&rdquo; and large gestures Leonardo da Vinci used to tell the Gospel story in his beloved fresco</p>
    
     <p><em>Solar Dance</em> Modris Eksteins </p>
    <p>How Vincent van Gogh&mdash;who died penniless and ignored in 1890&mdash;became the iconic painter of the 20th century says more about us than about him</p>
    
     <p><em>Joseph Anton</em> Salman Rushdie  </p>
    <p>The author&rsquo;s account of his years in hiding is a dispiriting reminder of victories won by anti-free-speech violence</p>
    
      <p><em>From The Ruins Of Empire</em> Pankaj Mishra  </p>
    <p>In 1900, the West ruled most of the East, while in 2000, China and India were great powers: for Mishra, the real story of the last century is the resurrection of Asia</p>
    
      <p><em>A Geography Of Blood</em> Candace Savage  </p>
    <p>A scarifying tale about the bloody destruction of Western Canada&rsquo;s human and natural ecology in the latter 19th century and the way we still avert our eyes from it</p>
    
      <p><em>When I Was A Child I Read Books</em>  Marilynne Robinson  </p>
    <p>Humane and unfailingly civil essays marked by a high regard for the self as moral agent, and hence for every individual, by the eminent American writer</p>
    
      <p><em>Floating Gold</em> Christopher Kemp  </p>
    <p>Everything about ambergris cries out for investigation by an obsessed scientist who can write well: Kemp delivers wonderfully</p>
    
    
      <p><em>The Lifespan Of A Fact</em> John D&rsquo;Agata and Jim Fingal  </p>
    <p>A faceoff between writer and fact checker produces both high comedy and thoughtful debate about the difference, if any, between &ldquo;accuracy&rdquo; and &ldquo;truth&rdquo;</p>
    
     <p><em>Why Be Happy When You Could Be Normal?</em> Jeanette Winterson  </p>
    <p>You&rsquo;ve never met a mother quite like the one this celebrated novelist describes. Winterson&rsquo;s remarkable against-all-odds memoir will stay in your mind for a long time</p>
    
     <p><em>Behind The Beautiful Forevers: Life, Death,  And Hope In A Mumbai Undercity</em> Katherine Boo </p>
    <p>A widely acclaimed feat of reporting from a Pulitzer Prize-winning author</p>
    
    
      <p><em>The Victory Lab: The Secret Science Of Winning Campaigns</em> Sasha Issenberg  </p>
    <p>A fascinating look at how U.S. strategists, especially in Obama&rsquo;s campaign, used the latest social science research to make their efforts more effective</p>
    
      <p><em>Iron Curtain: The Crushing Of Eastern Europe</em> Anne Applebaum  </p>
    <p>The subjugation of tens of millions of Europeans is chronicled by the author of the bestselling Gulag with the same methodical determination</p>
    
      <p><em>Pharmageddon</em> David Healy  </p>
    <p>Neuropharmacologist David Healy&rsquo;s expos&eacute; of the pharmaceutical industry&rsquo;s control of modern medicine is a chilling, essential read</p>
    
     <p><em>Let The Eastern Bastards Freeze In The Dark</em> Mary Janigan  </p>
    <p>An entertaining history of Western alienation in Canada, more than ever an important and little-understood driver of national politics. </p>
    
    <p>Fiction </p>
    
    <p><em>Dear Life: Stories</em> Alice Munro  </p>
    <p>It&rsquo;s Alice Munro. What else is there to say? A wonderful Christmas present from our internationally renowned literary star.</p>
    
      <p><em>Carry The One</em> Carol Anshaw  </p>
    <p>With wit and poetic insight, Anshaw traces the lives  of intersecting characters united by a tragic car crash</p>
    
      <p><em>Gone Girl</em> Gillian Flynn  </p>
    <p>Flynn&rsquo;s razor-sharp, enthralling tale of a wife gone AWOL kick-starts a new genre: marital thriller</p>
    
     <p><em>Lenin&rsquo;s Kisses</em> Yan Liank  </p>
    <p>Lianke channels Jonathan Swift and David Foster Wallace in this epic, poetic and grotesque satire of  life in modern China</p>
    
      <p><em>The Purchase</em> Linda Spalding  </p>
    <p>Winner of the 2012 Governor General&rsquo;s Literary Award for fiction, this is a stunning, beautifully written multi-generational novel about slavery and the human spirit</p>
    
     <p><em>The Land Of Decoration</em> Grace McCleen  </p>
    <p>This intimate debut novel about an imaginative 10-year-old can be harrowing to read, but in this book, McCleen has pulled off a small miracle</p>
    
    </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Help</sections>
    
  <body.head>
    <hedline>The embarrassment of riches</hedline>
    
    <abstract>If you think the wealthy don&rsquo;t have money problems, you&rsquo;re wrong</abstract>
    
    <byline>Julia McKinnell</byline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_MONEYMERGE.jpg"></photo>
  <photo.caption>Something has come between us: Wealthy couples can often mistake gifts and material goods as a substitute for love and intimacy</photo.caption>
    
  <photo.byline>photo illustration by sarah mackinnon</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
    <p>When couples fight about money, it isn&rsquo;t always because they don&rsquo;t have enough. In many cases, the more they have, the more dysfunction there is, says Deborah Price, a well-respected money coach and author of a new book for couples called <em>The Heart of Money: A Couple&rsquo;s Guide to Creating True Financial Intimacy</em>. </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;This book was written for anybody who&rsquo;s interested in exploring and understanding their more emotional and behavioural issues toward money,&rdquo; said Price, the California-based founder and CEO of the Money Coaching Institute. &ldquo;Many of our clients are people who are very affluent. In fact, many are from multi-generational families of wealth.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Price&rsquo;s coaching work goes beyond financial advice to help people talk about what&rsquo;s really going on. &ldquo;For example, I have a client who is very talented and makes a good living, but who worries incessantly about money. He thinks he has money issues, but the truth is, he has enough money and makes a good living. His real problems are: one, he hates what he does for a living and feels trapped; two, he lacks the confidence and faith that he can choose to do something else; and three, he doesn&rsquo;t believe that he deserves to have what he wants, which is the heart of his problem,&rdquo; writes Price. </p>
    
    <p>On the phone, she acknowledges that &ldquo;a lot of people don&rsquo;t have a lot of compassion for the wealthy, but the fact is, they sometimes have very painful stories.&rdquo; Price also runs a workshop where the rich learn to talk about love and wealth. &ldquo;A person can develop a way of thinking &lsquo;when you love me, you give me something,&rsquo; which is a flawed way of seeing love, but is actually a really common dynamic amongst wealthy people.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Children from wealthy families often lack self-esteem, she adds. &ldquo;They feel guilty because they have all this money and they haven&rsquo;t had to work for it. And/or they grew up in dysfunctional systems where money was used as a means of control or manipulation. I can&rsquo;t tell you how many wealthy children I work with as adults who got everything they could possibly ever imagine in the material realm, but did not experience love and affection. So they grow up with another level of deprivation . There&rsquo;s not a lot of sensitivity or compassion for them&mdash;because they have so much&mdash;that they can feel alone in the world.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Exploring your childhood experience with money is central to understanding your current relationship to it, says Price, who asks clients, whether wealthy or struggling financially, to write a money biography. &ldquo;Write your stories from your earliest money memory and move chronologically through time. It is best to write your money story in a stream-of-consciousness manner without editing, judging or analyzing your memories,&rdquo; she instructs in the book. </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;I&rsquo;m not a therapist. I&rsquo;m a coach,&rdquo; she says, explaining that behaviours related to money start when we are children, and so her coaching has to look to the past. </p>
    
    <p>In the book, she describes how she helped saved the marriage of a multi-millionaire whose wife was ready to divorce him. The husband ran a successful biotech firm but was often away on business, obsessed with amassing more and more money. When the wife asked for a divorce, the husband said, &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve given you everything&mdash;look at this house, this life.&rdquo; The wife responded, &ldquo;I didn&rsquo;t get married to this house or this life. I married you, and you barely exist in this relationship, and this isn&rsquo;t the life I ever wanted.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>After working with Price, the husband realized he had an unconscious desire to prove his father&mdash;who said he wouldn&rsquo;t amount to anything&mdash;wrong. &ldquo;He decided to sell his company and focus on his home life for a while, while the family lived off the investments,&rdquo; she writes. &ldquo;They  are planning to start a family foundation to help make a difference in the lives of single mothers, a cause close to the wife&rsquo;s heart.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>In the interview, Price points out that the phrase &ldquo;money is the root of all evil&rdquo; is a misquotation from the Bible, and it&rsquo;s the emotional connection to it that does the damage. &ldquo;The love of money is the root of all evil,&rdquo; she corrects. </p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Feschuk</sections>
    
  <body.head>
    <hedline>Let the Liberal blood sport begin</hedline>
    
    <abstract>The leadership candidates try to rise above Canada&rsquo;s Saddest Fundraising Campaign</abstract>
    
  <byline>Scott Feschuk</byline>
  
    </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_FESCHUKMERGE.jpg"></photo>
  <photo.caption>Me love guns: Trudeau&rsquo;s strategy for making amends to offended Albertans hinges on saying nice things about guns. Next: his favourite Rambo movies</photo.caption>
    
  <photo.byline>photo illustration by taylor shute</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>The Liberal leadership race is really heating up. First, David Bertschi tweeted, &ldquo;I had a nice day in North Bay.&rdquo; Then Martha Hall Findlay tweeted, &ldquo;Just had a terrific meeting in Edmonton.&rdquo; Truly, this contest is turning into a blood sport. </p>
    
    <p>For those who&rsquo;ve lost track, there are now 3,200 people running to be leader of the Liberal party: Justin Trudeau, Deborah Coyne, the three people sitting with you right now in the dentist&rsquo;s waiting room, the Professor, Mary Ann&mdash;the list keeps growing. The field is so crowded that the party has pretty much no choice but to hold its policy debates on one of those conveyor belts they have in some sushi restaurants. <em>Ms. Findlay, you have 20 seconds to answer this question before you disappear into the kitchen for half an hou</em>r. </p>
    
    <p>The significant interest in the job of leader sounds a positive note for the future of the party. In news that doesn&rsquo;t do that, interim leader Bob Rae sent out an email this week basically begging Liberal supporters to donate $5. That&rsquo;s right&mdash;five whole dollars. Not interested? Bob is willing to sweeten the deal. Hand over the five-spot and in return you&rsquo;ll get . . . a copy of his holiday card! Just contact the Liberal party and ask to contribute to Canada&rsquo;s Saddest Fundraising Campaign. </p>
    
    <p>But back to the leadership. In a crowded field, the challenge is finding a way to stand out. Karen McCrimmon has an interesting background&mdash;the first woman to command a Canadian air force squadron&mdash;and a unique take on why Canadians have traditionally resisted political extremism. &ldquo;Maybe,&rdquo; she said, &ldquo;it is because we routinely face the extremes of weather, of distance and of geography.&rdquo; I&rsquo;m not sure I follow: we aren&rsquo;t fascists because the meetings are far away and it&rsquo;s cold out? </p>
    
    <p>Also new on the scene is George Takach, a candidate that has been described by many Liberals as: &ldquo;Who?&rdquo; Turns out Takach is a lawyer and self-professed computer geek who views technology as the key to democratic reform. </p>
    
    <p>&ldquo;Imagine,&rdquo; Takach said, &ldquo;if on every [piece of legislation] you had a meaningful, Wikipedia kind of discussion going on . . . &rdquo; Okay, let&rsquo;s imagine that. Let&rsquo;s imagine thousands of the reasonable, well-informed people we find on the Internet taking the time to advance the kind of detailed, well-supported positions we often see on comment boards. Just imagine how House of Commons bills could be improved by the inclusion of clauses like, &ldquo;Harper sucks eggs!&rdquo; and &ldquo;Get Viagra here cheap!&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Like several other candidates for the leadership, Takach has never been elected to political office&mdash;but he insists that&rsquo;s not a drawback. And why would it be?<em> People of Canada, I don&rsquo;t understand &ldquo;government.&rdquo; I have no experience in any realm of elected public policy. I&rsquo;m almost positive this &ldquo;Governor General&rdquo; I hear so much about is one of the characters from the board game Clue. But please vote for me to be your Premium Minister&mdash;or whatever it&rsquo;s called</em>. </p>
    
    <p>Meanwhile, Justin Trudeau is still trying to recover from his 2010 remark about how powerful people from Alberta are ruining Canada with their general, all-round Albertaness. Justin&rsquo;s strategy for making amends to Albertans apparently hinges on saying positive things about guns. He criticized the federal long-gun registry as a &ldquo;failure&rdquo;&mdash;even though he voted to save it. And he spoke about his fond memory of hiking through Greenland with a rifle as protection from polar bears. We&rsquo;re at most a few days away from him holding a press conference to rate his favourite Rambo movies, one through four. </p>
    
    <p>You probably read that Marc Garneau recently joined the race. But did you know that Garneau was, at one point in his career, an <em>astronaut?</em> I bring this up in case you hadn&rsquo;t noticed him repeatedly mentioning that he was an astronaut. Or heard him make that &ldquo;rocket science&rdquo; joke he makes. Or discovered that the slogan for his campaign is: &ldquo;Let&rsquo;s take Canada to new heights.&rdquo; Get it? <em>Heights? </em>Because: astronaut! </p>
    
    <p>Competing with a candidate who was an astronaut (Marc Garneau&mdash;hadn&rsquo;t you heard?) may sound overwhelming, but Vancouver MP Joyce Murray has him beat. In kicking off her campaign, Murray casually mentioned, &ldquo;I am someone who sees the future and seizes it.&rdquo; Got that? She doesn&rsquo;t just predict the future. She doesn&rsquo;t guesstimate it. She actually sees the future. </p>
    
    <p>Your move, spaceman.</p>

   </body.content>
    
    
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>The End</sections>
    
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Ron Lloyd Mackintosh, 1948-2012</hedline>
    
    <abstract>He&rsquo;d recently retired to Mexico, his &lsquo;utopia.&rsquo; Safety conscious, he chose a walled compound in a quiet region he knew well.</abstract>
    
    <byline>Jane Armstrong</byline>
    
  </body.head>
    
  <photo href="file://images/MAC50_THE_ENDMERGE.jpg"></photo>
  <photo.byline>illustration by ted mcgrath</photo.byline>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Ron Lloyd Mackintosh was born Aug. 24, 1948, in Toronto, to Don Mackintosh, an accountant, and Dorine, a homemaker. Ron, an only child, was close to his cousin Dan Sutton, a year his junior. They spent summers at the Mackintosh cottage at Wasaga Beach on Georgian Bay, where the boys swam and hiked and camped overnight in tents on the beach.  </p>
    
    <p>Ron loved comic books, ghost stories and playing pranks on his cousins. Once, he switched the black licorice sticks Dan hid under his pillow with red pieces. &ldquo;We couldn&rsquo;t figure out why the licorice changed to red,&rdquo; Dan says. &ldquo;He had us believing that ghosts did it.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Every Easter, Ron joined Dan&rsquo;s family in Clearwater, Fla., for a month-long holiday. The cousins swam every day in the motel pool. &ldquo;He loved the heat,&rdquo; says Dan. &ldquo;Always. He hated being cold.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Ron&rsquo;s mother was strict with her only son, but Don was more easy-going. Ron and Don played chess and shot pool in the basement of their Eglinton Avenue West house in north Toronto. In the backyard, there was a giant slide, which Ron and Dan polished with waxed paper to make it more slippery. </p>
    
    <p>After high school, Ron travelled to Europe and later moved to San Francisco, where he managed a health-food restaurant. But he returned to Toronto in the early 1970s and began training as an engineering surveyor. In 1975, he joined M.M. Dillon Ltd., a construction firm that built infrastructure projects such as highways, tunnels and railway overpasses. Ron was a project supervisor, overseeing the contractor&rsquo;s work. In Dillon&rsquo;s Windsor, Ont., office, he met Joan Jobin, with whom he shared a love for the West Coast. When he landed a job as an inspector for Associated Engineering in Nanaimo, B.C., in 1981, he moved to Vancouver Island. Joan followed a year later. They married in 1984, the same year their son, Adam, was born. Four years later, daughter Kala arrived. </p>
    
    <p>In 1987, Ron&rsquo;s boss, Tony Koers, started his own company, Koers and Associates Engineering, and he hired Ron as chief inspector. Ron supervised some of the biggest infrastructure projects on Vancouver Island, including the expansion of the Qualicum Beach Airport and the development of an 18-hole golf course and residential development in Nanoose Bay. </p>
    
    <p>Ron, who was always safety conscious, was skilled at diffusing conflicts on a construction site, says Tony. &ldquo;He resolved issues&mdash;staved them off before they became a problem.&rdquo;  </p>
    
    <p>Ron&rsquo;s job took him away from home for months on end, and the long separations ate away at family life. But in 1992, the family took a three-week vacation to Melaque, a small Mexican town on the Pacific Coast. All-inclusive resorts weren&rsquo;t for Ron, so he left a week before to scout a nice vacation spot. He rented a hut right on the beach, Joan says. </p>
    
    <p>In 1996, Ron and Joan separated. The split mystified relatives and devastated Joan. &ldquo;He walked out the door,&rdquo; she says. &ldquo;That was pretty shocking for all of us. We were not expecting that.&rdquo; Ron&rsquo;s relationship with Adam and Kala faltered too. &ldquo;I know he loved his kids,&rdquo; says Joan. &ldquo;I think he did the best he could.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Eight years ago, Ron met Marie Halliday. During winter construction breaks, he&rsquo;d return to Melaque with his camera for weeks on end. His friend Brian MacDonald says Mexico was a refuge&mdash;&ldquo;his own little utopia.&rdquo; &ldquo;Ron was a bit averse to structure. He just loved the fact that he could go down there and find a larger sense of freedom.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>In 2010, Ron, then retired, packed his bags and drove to Melaque in his Jeep Patriot. He plotted his route carefully to avoid the worst crime-plagued regions, says David Regehr, a friend who made the drive with Ron. &ldquo;He never stopped for broken-down cars.&rdquo; </p>
    
    <p>Marie joined him a few months later. They rented a walled, two-storey house a block from the beach. He was happy and relaxed, although security was a concern. </p>
    
    <p>Still, &ldquo;he was where he wanted to be,&rdquo; Brian says. Ron adopted a stray dog, Nicco, who accompanied Ron around town in his Jeep. Last year, Kala came to visit for a month. He wrote friends in B.C. that he was thrilled to reconnect with his daughter. </p>
    
    <p>Earlier this year, he and Marie moved to Barra de Navidad, a few kilometres southeast of Melaque. On Oct. 21, Ron left the house to visit a friend. He vanished on the drive home. His body was found beside a tree near Barra de Navidad. He&rsquo;d been strangled. His dog and Jeep have not been found.</p>
    
  </body.content>
    
</body>

</catalog>